AND GOOD AFTERNOON WELCOME TO THE SEPTEMBER 9TH 2025 REGULAR
MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO PRESENT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR OF MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
PRESENTS SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT MANAGEMENT PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR
WALTON PRESENT WALTON PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE
PRESENT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE RAMA TO SALONI
WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS
LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE DRAMATIST
ALONE WE HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM
LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE ROMITA SALONI COMMUNITY AND BY
AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I
WOULD LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV
PARTICULARLY TODAY KALEENA MENDOZA THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? >> MR. PRESIDENT SPECIAL ORDER
AT 2 P.M.. OKAY WELL LET'S GO TO OUR 2
P.M. SPECIAL ORDER SPECIAL ORDER AT 2 P.M. IS THE
APPEARANCE AT TODAY'S MEETING BY THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL
MURRAY PRESENT TO ENGAGE IN A FORMAL POLICY DISCUSSION WITH
ELIGIBLE BOARD MEMBERS. PRIOR TO THE DISCUSSION THE
MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE BOARD FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES.
>> WELCOME, MR. MAYOR. DO YOU HAVE ANY OPENING
REMARKS? >> THANK YOU.
BOARD PRESIDENT. I.
I WANT TO SAY I MISSED YOU ALL. I HOPE YOU GOT SOME GOOD DOWN
TIME EARLIER TODAY AT UNION SQUARE.
I ANNOUNCED MY HEART OF THE CITY EXECUTIVE DIRECTIVE TO
MAKE DOWNTOWN A 24 SEVEN NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE YOU CAN
LIVE, WORK, PLAY AND LEARN. DOWNTOWN IS THE HEART OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND OUR JOB IS TO BRING IT MORE FULLY BACK TO
LIFE. THAT MEANS MORE HOUSING, MORE
JOBS, MORE CULTURE AND MORE LEARNING ON HOUSING WITH
PRESIDENT ADELMAN AND THIS BOARD'S SUPPORT.
WE'RE CREATING A DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION FINANCIAL
DISTRICT TO MAKE OFFICE TO RESIDENTIAL CONVERSIONS EASIER
TURNING EMPTY TOWERS INTO NEW HOMES.
ON JOBS WE'RE CREATING CONDITIONS TO MAKE DOWNTOWN THE
PREMIER DESTINATION FOR EMPLOYERS AND EMPLOYEES.
THROUGH PERMIT S.F. WE'RE STREAMLINING PERMITS FOR NEW
OFFICES AND SMALL BUSINESSES AND WE'RE MODERNIZING OUR
OFFICE STOCK TO ATTRACT NEW COMPANIES AND CULTURE.
WE'RE ACTIVATING PUBLIC SPACES AND EXPANDING NIGHTLIFE.
EXPECT MORE FREE CONCERTS, MORE ART, MORE ENTERTAINMENT ZONES
ACROSS DOWNTOWN SUPPORTED BY PHILANTHROPIC INVESTMENT.
STATE LEGISLATION AND STATE LEGISLATION FOR ADDITIONAL
LIQUOR LICENSE. AND EVEN EASIER PERMITTING ON
EDUCATION WE'RE WORKING TO BRING MORE UNIVERSAL KEYS
AND INSTITUTIONS DOWNTOWN CREATING OPPORTUNITIES FOR
YOUNG PEOPLE AND HELPING ANCHOR THE NEIGHBORHOOD'S FUTURE.
THIS EFFORT IS ALREADY UNDERWAY IN THE FIRST 100 DAYS.
WE'VE SECURED OVER $40 MILLION IN PRIVATE SECTOR COMMITMENTS
TO BEAUTIFY OUR STREETS. SUPPORT SMALL BUSINESSES
AND ACTIVATE PLAZAS AND CORRIDORS.
IN THE NEXT SIX MONTHS WILL OPEN APPLICATIONS FOR
CONVERSION PROJECTS, LAUNCH NEW ENTERTAINMENT ZONES, ATTRACT
NEW RETAILERS AND ESTABLISH A NEW PARK IN THE EAST.
CUT. AND WITHIN A YEAR WILL BREAK
GROUND ON MAJOR PLACEMAKING PROJECTS AND ALIGN CITY
PROPERTIES WITH OUR REVITALIZATION GOALS.
TOGETHER THESE REFORMS HOUSING ,BUSINESS INCENTIVES, CULTURAL
INVESTMENTS AND EDUCATION FORM A COORDINATED STRATEGY TO
RESTORE RESTORE THE HEART OF OUR CITY.
DOWNTOWN BELONGS TO EVERY SAN FRANCISCAN.
THE ECONOMIC GENERATED IN DOWNTOWN POWER IS MUNI FUNDS
OUR PARKS PAYS OUR FIRST RESPONDERS AND SUSTAINS
CRITICAL SERVICES THAT HELP FAMILIES THRIVE.
WITH THIS DIRECTIVE WE ARE BUILDING A DOWNTOWN THAT WILL
THRIVE FOR GENERATIONS TO COME .
I WANT TO THANK THE DOWNTOWN DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION FOR
PARTNERING WITH US TO MAKE THESE ECONOMIC INVESTMENTS
POSSIBLE. AND THIS BOARD FOR APPROVING MY
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT BEHEST AND PAYMENT WAIVERS THAT
ENABLES THIS WORK. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU, MAYOR LURIE. MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE
CALL THE TOPIC FOR DISTRICT SEVEN?
>> YES. THE TOPIC SUBMITTED BY THE
MEMBER OF THE BOARD REPRESENTING DISTRICT SEVEN
SUPERVISOR MELGAR IS THE FAMILY HOUSING PLAN.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR, SINCE YOUR OPENING QUESTION THANK
YOU, PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU MAYOR FOR BEING
HERE WITH US TODAY. I HOPE THAT YOU HAD A GOOD
BREAK WITH YOUR FAMILY AS WELL. I KNOW WE ALL NEEDED THE BREAK
AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR COMMITMENT TO MEETING OUR
CITY'S HOUSING CRISIS HEAD ON WITH YOUR PROPOSED FAMILY
HOUSING PLAN PARTICULARLY AS IT AFFECTS THE WEST SIDE PART OF
WHICH I REPRESENT IN THE MEETINGS THAT I HAVE ATTENDED
AND YOU, YOUR AND YOUR STAFF HAVE ATTENDED AS WELL.
>> PEOPLE HAVE BROUGHT UP SOME ISSUES CONSISTENTLY THAT THEY
SEE AS CHALLENGES WITH A PLAN AND I WOULD LIKE TO HEAR YOUR
IDEAS AND YOUR COMMITMENT TO INCLUDING SPECIFIC LEGISLATION
OR TWO WORKING WITH US TO SUPPORT OTHERS LEGISLATION
ADDRESSING SOME OF THESE ISSUES.
SO FOR ME THESE ISSUES INCLUDE THE POTENTIAL DISPLACEMENT OF
SMALL BUSINESSES THE RESIDENTIAL TENANT DISPLACEMENT
DUE TO DEMOLITION OF RENT CONTROLLED UNITS AND AND THE
LACK OF DEDICATED FUNDING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING WHICH HAS
NOT BEEN BUILT ON THE WEST SIDE FOR A VERY LONG TIME AT IT
CERTAINLY NOT AT THE SAME PACE AS IN THE EASTERN NEIGHBORHOODS
AND IT IS SORELY NEEDED. WE HAVE BETTER SCHOOLS.
WE HAVE BETTER PARKS. IT'S AN OPPORTUNITY FOR PEOPLE.
SO I WOULD ASK YOU TO PLEASE SHARE SPECIFIC IDEAS THAT YOU
HAVE AND AS TO THE PLAN AND HOW TO ADDRESS EACH OF THOSE
ISSUES. >> I APPRECIATE THAT
OPPORTUNITY AND SUPERVISORS AND SAN FRANCISCANS ARE RIGHT
TO ASK TOUGH QUESTIONS ABOUT WHAT THE FAMILY ZONING WILL
MEAN FOR OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. LET ME BE CLEAR WE WILL NOT
LEAVE SMALL BUSINESSES, RENTERS OR AFFORDABLE HOUSING BEHIND.
FAMILY ZONING WILL STRENGTHEN, NOT WEAKEN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
THAT MEANS PROTECTING SMALL BUSINESSES, SAFEGUARDING
RENTERS, PRESERVING WHAT MAKES OUR COMMUNITIES SPECIAL
AND BUILDING REAL AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
WE KNOW FROM EXPERIENCE THAT MOST NEW HOUSING IS BUILT ON
VACANT LOTS AND SITES LIKE GAS STATIONS OR SHUTTERED
COMMERCIAL SPACES NOT SPACES WITH THRIVING BUSINESSES.
STILL SMALL BUSINESS SMALL BUSINESSES KNOW CONSTRUCTION
CAN BE DISRUPTIVE AND THEY ARE THE LIFEBLOOD OF OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS. THAT'S WHY I'M PROUD TO SUPPORT
YOUR LEGISLATION. SUPERVISOR MELGAR CREATING A
SMALL BUSINESS REZONING CONSTRUCTION RELIEF FUND.
THIS WILL ENABLE GRANTS AND LOANS TO BUSINESSES
IMPACTED BY NEW HOUSING CONSTRUCTION AND CONNECT SMALL
BUSINESSES WITH OTHER SERVICES LIKE LEASING SUPPORT
AND FINANCIAL COUNSELORS TO HELP THEM STAY AFLOAT.
I'M ALSO HAPPY TO SUPPORT THE RECOMMENDATIONS FROM OUR SMALL
BUSINESS COMMUNITY INCLUDING EARLY NOTIFICATION OF
BUSINESSES WHEN NEW HOUSING IS PROPOSED AND INCENTIVES FOR
PROVIDING COMMERCIAL TENANT IMPROVEMENTS AND NEW RETAIL
SPACE. SAN FRANCISCO HAS AMONG THE
STRONGEST TENANT PROTECTIONS IN THE COUNTRY AND THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT HAS BEEN WORKING WITH SUPERVISOR CHEN TO MAKE
THEM EVEN STRONGER. I WANT TO BE CRYSTAL CLEAR HERE
. DEMOLITION OF RENT CONTROLLED
HOUSING IS EXTRAORDINARILY RARE.
FURTHER WHEN DEMOLITION DOES OCCUR EXIST ING LAWS REQUIRE
ONE FOR ONE REPLACEMENT UNITS. AND WE WILL GO FURTHER.
SUPERVISOR MAL GARS PROPOSAL WILL GIVE HOUSING DEVELOPERS AN
OPTION NOT TO JUST REPLACE BUT TO ADD NEW RENT CONTROLLED
UNITS TO THEIR INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS WHILE PROTECTING
THE RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING THAT WE ALREADY HAVE.
IT'S TRUE AS YOU POINTED OUT THAT AFFORDABLE HOUSING HAS
BEEN CONCENTRATED IN SOME NEIGHBORHOODS ON THE EASTERN
AND SOUTHERN NEIGHBORHOODS FOR DECADES AND THAT HAS TO CHANGE.
IT'S ALSO TRUE THAT WE NEED STABLE ONGOING SOURCES OF
FUNDING. IF WE ARE GOING TO MEET OUR
AFFORDABILITY GOALS, THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN CREATES CAPACITY
FOR NEW HOUSING INCLUDING OPPORTUNITY SITES THAT ARE
OPTIMAL FOR 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR YOUR RESOLUTION TAKES THE NEXT STEP
BY URGING THE CITY TO EXPLORE INNOVATE INNOVATIVE FUNDING
TOOLS TO AFFORD BUILDING HOUSING IN WELL RESOURCED
NEIGHBORHOODS INCLUDING DEDICATED FUNDING FROM FUTURE
PROPERTY TAX GROWTH. SAN FRANCISCO MUST GROW BUT WE
MUST GROW FAIRLY. THESE MEASURES ENSURE THAT AS
WE WELCOME NEW NEIGHBORS WE ARE PROTECTING EXISTING TENANTS,
SUPPORTING SMALL BUSINESSES AND SECURING REAL FUNDING FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN EVERY PART OF OUR CITY.
FROM DAY ONE I HAVE SAID SAN FRANCISCO IS AT ITS BEST WHEN
THE MAYOR AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WORK TOGETHER.
AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR, HIS PROPOSALS SHOW HOW
COLLABORATION CAN DELIVER REAL SOLUTIONS.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR.
>> THANK YOU, MAYOR LURIE. SUPERVISOR MELGAR YOU MAY NOW
ASK A FOLLOW UP QUESTION DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE OPENING
QUESTION. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH
PRESIDENT MANDELL MEN AND THANK YOU FOR THAT REALLY THOUGHTFUL
ANSWER, MR. MAYOR. AT THE TENANT PROTECTIONS
IN THE PLAN ARE CURRENT ARE MODELED AFTER SB 330 AND SB 330
DOES NOT QUITE DO EVERYTHING THAT WE NEED IN PROTECTING RENT
CONTROLLED UNITS FROM DEMOLITION BECAUSE IT DOESN'T
REQUIRE LIKE FOR LIKE REPLACEMENT IT REQUIRES ONE FOR
ONE. >> BUT THERE'S NO GUARANTEE
THAT THE UNITS ARE RENTAL UNITS FOR ONE AND THE REQUIREMENT FOR
YOU KNOW, THE RIGHT OF FIRST REFUSAL IS ONLY FOR LOW INCOME
TENANTS. AND ONE OF THE FOUNDATIONAL
UNDERPINNINGS OF OUR OWN RENT CONTROL LAW IS THAT IT'S FOR
EVERYONE. AND SO THE LOOKBACK PERIOD FOR
TENANT HISTORY IS ONLY FIVE YEARS MEANING THAT OWNERS
COULD, YOU KNOW, JUST HANG ON TO THEIR PERMITS FOR A LITTLE
WHILE LONGER TO GET AROUND IT. SO I'M WORRIED ABOUT THAT.
I'M ALSO WORRIED ABOUT A DEDICATED SOURCE OF FUNDING FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AS I SAID, BECAUSE VERY LITTLE HAS BEEN
BUILT ON THE WEST SIDE. AND THERE'S ALSO POLITICAL
PUSHBACK EVERY TIME WE PROPOSE IT.
AND SO I WORRY THAT THERE WILL NOT BE ENOUGH WITH THE FUNDING
SOURCES THAT WE HAVE RIGHT NOW TO MEET THIS OBLIGATION FOR THE
WEST SIDE WHILE NOT HURTING THE EAST SIDE OF TOWN WHICH ALSO
HAS VERY SERIOUS AFFORDABLE HOUSING NEEDS.
SO ARE YOU COMMITTED TO WORKING FURTHER TO ADD PROTECTIONS TO
INCENTIVIZE RENTAL HOUSING CONSTRUCTION AND THE
PRESERVATION OF RENT CONTROLLED UNITS WHICH WE'RE LOSING EVERY
DAY AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING? I'LL BE VERY QUICK AND DIRECT
AND TO THE POINT AS A SUPERVISOR I AGREE THAT
PRESERVING OUR RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING STOCK IS ESSENTIAL TO
MAINTAINING AFFORDABILITY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND I COMMIT AND LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH YOU ON YOUR
FORTHCOMING TENANT PROTECTION PROPOSAL.
SO I THANK YOU FOR IT AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH
YOU ON IT. THANK YOU MAYOR.
THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR. YOU MAY NOW ASK IT KEEPS IN THE
BACK ON MR. MAYOR. YOU MAY NOW ASK A QUESTION TO
SUPERVISOR MELGAR OR TO ANY OTHER SUPERVISOR IN ATTENDANCE
PERTAINING TO THE SAME TOPIC BUT NOT NECESSARILY RELATED TO
THE PREVIOUS QUESTION. >> NO.
THANK YOU FOR HAVING ME TODAY AND I'LL LET YOU ALL GET DOWN
TO YOUR BUSINESS. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, SIR. >> APPRECIATE IT.
IF IT IS ALL RIGHT, THAT CONCLUDES OUR DISTRICT SEVEN
TOPIC DISCUSSION. >> THE MATTER HAS BEEN
DISCUSSED AND WILL BE FILED AFTER GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> MADAM CLERK, I THINK YOU MAY HAVE HAD OTHER COMMUNICATION.
YES. YES.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE AT THIS MEETING
IN ROOM 250 ON THE SECOND FLOOR WITHIN CITY HALL.
IF YOU ARE UNABLE TO MAKE IT DOWN TO THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE
CHAMBER, YOU MAY WATCH THE PROCEEDING ON S.F. GOVEE TV'S
CHANNEL 26 OR VIEW THE LIVE STREAM ON YOUR COMPUTER AT W W
W DOT S.F. GEO VTV.ORG. IF YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT YOUR
WRITING YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT AND WRITING YOU CAN SEND AN
EMAIL TO BOS AT S.F. GOV.ORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE JUST
ADDRESS YOUR ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. >> THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102
AND IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION
REQUEST UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR IF YOU
NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S
OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE AND YOU CAN DO
THAT BY CALLING (415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> LET'S GO TO THE APPROVAL OF
OUR MEETING MINUTES. YES.
APPROVAL OF THE JULY 29TH 2020 FIVE BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
>> COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED MOVED BY FIELD OR SECONDED BY MELGAR?
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
YES ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SOUDER SUTTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO ENGARDIO I AND SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I THERE ARE 11 EYES THEN WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR REGULAR AGENDA UNFINISHED
BUSINESS ITEM TWO THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO REVISE THE GOALS AND REPORTING
REQUIREMENTS FOR FOOD PURCHASING BY THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH AND THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT FOR CITY HOSPITALS
AND JAILS AND TO REVISE THE SUNSET DATE SUCH THAT THE
PROGRAM STANDARDS AND REPORTING REQUIREMENTS WILL REMAIN
IN EFFECT UNTIL DECEMBER 31ST 2035 PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEM TWO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR
MENDELSON HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I AND SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW
BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER THREE ITEM THREE THIS IS
AN ORDINANCE THAT AUTHORIZES THE EXECUTION AND DELIVERY OF
TAX EXEMPT OR TAXABLE CERTIFICATES OF PARTICIPATION
IN THE AMOUNT OF 65 MILLION TO FINANCE AND REFINANCE CERTAIN
CAPITAL IMPROVEMENT PROJECTS WITHIN THE CITY AND COUNTY AS
EVIDENCED IN THE CAPITAL PLAN AND TO APPROVE MULTIPLE
AGREEMENTS, FORMS, SUPPLEMENTS TO APPROVE THE FORM OF THE
OFFICIAL NOTICE OF SALE AND A NOTICE OF INTENTION TO SELL THE
CERTIFICATES TO APPROVE THE FORM OF AN OFFICIAL STATEMENT
IN PRELIMINARY AND FINAL FORM THE FORM OF THE PURCHASE
CONTRACT BETWEEN THE CITY AND ONE OR MORE INITIAL
PURCHASERS OF THE CERTIFICATES AND THE CONTINUING DISCLOSURE
CERTIFICATE. AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER FOUR ITEM FOUR RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZE THE OFFICE OF THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE $167,000 GRANT FROM THE
SUPERIOR COURT OF CALIFORNIA COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR THE
GRANT TERM OF SEPTEMBER FIRST, 2024 THROUGH AUGUST 31ST 2026
TO SUPPORT THE BURN STATE CRISIS INTERVENTION PROGRAM
ACTIVITIES AND SERVICES SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE FOURTH AMENDMENT TO THE
AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND PROJECT OPEN HAND TO
PROVIDE HIV AND AIDS FOOD AND NUTRITION SERVICES TO
INCREASE THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY 1.7 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL OF
20.5 MILLION WITH NO CHANGES TO THE TERM NOW APRIL 1ST, 2017
THROUGH MARCH 31ST 2027 AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE
SAN FRANCISCO DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ENTER INTO AN
AGREEMENT WITH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF STATE HOSPITALS
TO PROVIDE FUNDING FOR THE FELONY INCOMPETENT TO STAND
TRIAL MENTAL HEALTH DIVERSION PROGRAM FOR A FIVE YEAR TERM
JULY 1ST, 2025 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2030 HAVING ANTICIPATED
REVENUE OF APPROXIMATELY 15 MILLION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
SEVEN AND EIGHT TOGETHER. >> ITEM SEVEN AND EIGHT ARE TO
RESOLUTIONS THAT APPROVE TWO REAL PROPERTY LEASES FOR ITEM
SEVEN THIS APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE DIRECTOR OF
PROPERTY TO LEASE APPROXIMATELY 4000FT2 OF REAL PROPERTY FOR
THE PUBLIC DEFENDER'S OFFICE LOCATED AT EIGHT BOARDMAN PLACE
FOR A FIVE YEAR TERM WITH TWO FIVE YEAR OPTIONS TO EXTEND AT
95% OF FAIR MARKET VALUE AT AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF 144,000
FROM STEEL ARC LLC AND FOR ITEM EIGHT THIS AUTHORIZES
AND APPROVES THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO EXECUTE A LEASE
AGREEMENT FOR A FOUR YEAR TERM AND THREE FIVE YEAR OPTIONS TO
EXTEND WITH INPUT INC FOR THE CONTINUED USE OF THE OLD MINT
LOCATED AT 88 FIFTH STREET PAYING AS PARTICIPATION RENT
10% OF THE GROSS MONTHLY REVENUE GENERATED FROM THEIR
USE OF THE OLD MINT SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER NINE ITEM NINE RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE AN AGREEMENT WITH SOLARIS BUS U.S. INC TO PROCURE
THREE 40 FOOT AND THREE 60 FOOT BATTERY ELECTRIC TRANSIT BUSSES
FROM SOLARIS BUS UC INC ALONG WITH THE ASSOCIATED SPARE PARTS
SPECIAL TOOLS, MANUALS AND TRAINING THROUGH A SIGNED
OPTIONS ESTABLISHED UNDER A PROCUREMENT CONDUCTED BY KING
COUNTY METRO WITH AN ANTICIPATED EXPENDITURE OF 10.8
MILLION WHICH INCLUDES A CONTRACT FOR AN AMOUNT OF 9.9
MILLION AND A TERM THROUGH DECEMBER 19TH 2012 THEN WITH
OPTIONS TO EXTEND THE CONTRACT TO DECEMBER 19TH, 2029
AND RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE PAYMENT OF AN ESTIMATED 855,000
IN TAXES. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS TEN THROUGH 12 TOGETHER ITEM TEN
ITEMS TEN THROUGH THROUGH 12 ARE THREE RESOLUTIONS THAT
PERTAIN TO THE BALBOA RESERVOIR PARK PLAN AND AUTHORIZES THE
DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT FOR ITEM TEN APPROVES
AND AUTHORIZES FOR THE PURPOSES OF THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODE OF
1986 AS AMENDED THE EXECUTION AND DELIVERY OF MULTIFAMILY
HOUSING REVENUE NOTES OF APPROXIMATELY 84.1 MILLION TO
PROVIDE FINAL FINANCING FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF A 127 UNIT
MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING PROJECT EXPECTED TO BE LOCATED
AT 505 MAYOR EDWIN M LEE AVENUE, FORMERLY KNOWN AS 11
FRIDA KAHLO WAY KNOWN AS THE BALBOA RESERVOIR BUILDING E TO
APPROVE THE FORMS, AGREEMENTS, TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF THE
LOAN, THE EXECUTION AND DELIVERY OF THE NOTE THE
PROJECTED LOAN AND REGULATORY AGREEMENT AND DECLARATION OF
RESTRICTIVE COVENANTS TO AUTHORIZE THE COLLECTION OF
CERTAIN FEES TO APPROVE MODIFICATIONS CHANGES
AND ADDITIONS TO THE DOCUMENTS TO RATIFY AND APPROVE ANY
ACTIONS THUS FAR TAKEN IN CONNECTION WITH THE BACK TO
BACK LOANS. THE NOTE AND THE PROJECT FOR
ITEM 11 THIS ITEM EXECUTES AN AMENDED RESTATED LOAN AGREEMENT
WITH THE B C BALBOA BUILDERS LLC FOR AN APPROXIMATE LOAN
AMOUNT OF 56.4 MILLION TO FINANCE THE FIRST PHASE OF
INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROVEMENTS RELATED TO THE REVITALIZE ATION
AND MASTER DEVELOPMENT OF AN APPROXIMATE 17.6 ACRE SIZE
COMPLETE WITH VARIOUS PUBLIC BENEFITS SUCH AS AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AND TO ADOPT THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
AND FOR ITEM 12 HERE THIS AUTHORIZES A GROUND LEASE FOR
REAL PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY AND LOCATED AT 11 FRIDA KAHLO
WAY WITH BALBOA LEE AVENUE LP AS DEVELOPER FOR A LEASE TERM
OF 75 YEARS AND 124 YEAR OPTION TO EXTEND AND AN ANNUAL BASE
RENT OF 15,000 TO CONSTRUCT A 100% AFFORDABLE 127 UNIT
MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING DEVELOPMENT AFFORDABLE TO VERY
LOW AND LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS TO APPROVE AN AUTHORIZED AN
AMENDED AND RESTATED LOAN AGREEMENT IN AN AMOUNT OF 28
MILLION FOR A 57 YEAR LOAN TERM TO FINANCE THE DEVELOPMENT
AND CONSTRUCTION OF THE PROJECT AND FOR THE PROJECTS TO ADOPT
THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> CHURCH AND THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMANDA AND COLLEAGUES THIS HAS WE NEED TO MAKE AN
AMENDMENT THAT WAS NOT QUITE READY AT THE BUDGET COMMITTEE
BUT WAS DISCUSSED AND RECOMMENDED BY THE BUDGET
LEGISLATIVE ANALYST WHEN IT WAS AT THE COMMITTEE AND THE
AMENDMENT HAS BEEN SENT TO YOU ELECTRONICALLY AND IS FOR ITEM
NUMBER 11 AND THE FILE NUMBER IS 250829 AND THE AMENDMENTS
THAT WE WANTED TO MAKE TODAY IS ON PAGE FOUR LINE ONE TWO
ADDING A CLAUSE THAT INDICATING THAT EMIL CD HAS AGREED TO
PROVIDE A WRITTEN REPORTS TO THE POOR SUPERVISORS WITHIN THE
90 DAYS OF THE COMPLETION OF BUILDING E PARTICULARLY THIS IS
REALLY ABOUT TO REPORT BACK. WE ARE PROVIDING A LOAN TO THE
PROJECT AND AND WHETHER OR NOT THAT THE TOTAL DOES
DISBURSEMENTS OF THE PROPOSED INFRASTRUCTURE LOAN IS WHAT
WE'RE PROVIDING THE CITY'S PROVIDING AND WHETHER OR NOT
ANY ACTION HAS TAKEN TO FORGIVE ALL OR PART OF THE LOAN.
SO THAT'S WHAT WE WANT TO KNOW ULTIMATELY THIS IS A LONG
APPROVAL APPROVE A FULL VOE AND WE WANT TO KNOW IF WE END
UP FOR GIVING THE LOAN. SO WITH THAT I HOPE TO HAVE
YOUR SUPPORT ON THIS AMENDMENT .
>> THERE IS A MOTION FROM SUPERVISOR OR FROM CHAIR JAN TO
VOTE HERE. IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY
SUPERVISOR MELGAR? >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
SO MUCH. >> I JUST WANTED TO SAY THANK
YOU VERY MUCH TO CHAIR TRAN FOR HER WORK AND THOUGHTFULNESS ON
THIS AMENDMENT AND TO THE ENTIRE BUDGET COMMITTEE AND TO
EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING FOR
THEIR DILIGENT WORK ON THIS PROJECT.
>> IT'S BEEN LITERALLY 30 YEARS IN THE MAKING AND THE PERSON
THAT I ALSO WANT TO THANK IS MY DEAR FRIEND AND FORMER DISTRICT
SEVEN SUPERVISOR AND PRESIDENT AND MANY WHO WAS A SUPERVISOR
WITH THIS PROJECT WAS ENTITLED YOU MAY REMEMBER A COUPLE OF
YEARS AGO WE WE AMENDED THE DEVELOPMENT AGREEMENT TO HAVE
THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING GO FIRST AND THAT'S WHAT'S HAPPENING.
AND THIS INFRASTRUCTURE WILL SUPPORT PRIMARILY AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AS BEING BUILT FIRST BUT WILL SUPPORT THE PROJECT
OVERALL. SO I'M REALLY GRATEFUL THAT
WE'RE THERE AND ALSO AGAIN THANK YOU TO CHAIR TAN FOR HER
THOUGHTFULNESS AND FOR MOVING THIS FORWARD.
THANK YOU CHAIR CHAN AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR THERE'S A
MOTION THAT'S BEEN SECONDED. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT
WITHOUT OBJECTION. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE MOTION PASSES AND THEN I BELIEVE THAT WE CAN TAKE ITEMS
1011 AS AMENDED AND 12. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK LET'S LET GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 13 THROUGH 20 TOGETHER ITEM 13 THROUGH 20 WERE
CONSIDERED BY THE GOVERNMENT AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE
AT A REGULAR MEETING ON THURSDAY SEPTEMBER 4TH, 2025
AND WE'RE CONSIDERED AS COMMITTEE REPORTS HERE WE HAVE
EIGHT ORDINANCES THAT AUTHORIZE SETTLEMENT OF LAWSUIT FOR ITEM
13. THIS LAWSUIT WAS FILED BY
KATRINA BAPTIST INVOLVING AN EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE
AND AUTHORIZED TO SETTLE FOR 125,000 ITEM 14 FILED BY ILIANA
SHOW INVOLVING AN ALLEGED PERSONAL INJURY ON A CITY
SIDEWALK AND IS AUTHORIZED TO SETTLE FOR 225,000 ITEM 15 THIS
LAWSUIT WAS FILED BY JANE GISELA INVOLVING AN ALLEGED
PERSONAL INJURY ON A CITY SIDEWALK AND IS AUTHORIZED TO
SETTLE FOR 128,000. ITEM 16 CONTAINS THE
AUTHORIZATION TO SETTLE TWO LAWSUITS FILED BY KEITH BARAKA
INVOLVING AN EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE AND IS AUTHORIZED TO SETTLE FOR
160,000 FOR BOTH LAWSUITS. ITEM 17 WAS FILED BY THE
COALITION ON HOMELESSNESS. IT INVOLVES PLAINTIFFS
ALLEGATIONS THAT THE CITY UNLAWFULLY SEIZED PROPERTY
WITHOUT ADEQUATE ADVANCE NOTICE AND DISCARDS THE PROPERTY GOING
FORWARD. THE CITY SHOULD STORE UNDER
TERMS OF THE CITY'S BAG AND TAG POLICY IN A MANNER THAT ALLOWS
RETRIEVAL AND IS AUTHORIZED TO SETTLE FOR APPROXIMATELY 2.8
MILLION AND OTHER NON-MONETARY TERMS.
ITEM 18 THIS ORDINANCE IS A TO AUTHORIZE THE PARTIAL
SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED ON BEHALF OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY AND THE PEOPLE OF THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA AGAINST
THE TRUST FOR THE BENEFIT OF MEMBERS OF THE RAYMOND SACKLER
FAMILY FOR ABATEMENT FUNDS IN THE RANGE OF 8 TO 12 MILLION
TO BE PAID OVER 15 YEARS. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES
ALLEGATIONS THAT PURDUE AND THE SACKLERS CONTRIBUTED TO THE
OPIOID CRISIS BY INCENTIVIZING THE SALE AND USE OF OPIOIDS
DESPITE KNOWLEDGE OF THE GROWING EPIDEMIC CAUSED BY THE
MISUSE ITEM 19 FILED BY THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO ZERO ROGER SCHNEIDER AGAINST AT&T CORP AND PACIFIC
BELL TELEPHONE COMPANY FOR APPROXIMATELY 15.4 MILLION
AND FOR ITEM 20 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY THE CITY AND COUNTY EX-ROYAL ROGER
SCHNEIDER AGAINST U.S. TILAPIA CIVIC CORP DOING BUSINESS TPG
COMMUNICATIONS FOR 3.6 MILLION BOTH OF THESE SETTLEMENTS
INVOLVE THE ALLEGATIONS THAT BOTH AT&T AND TPG AND OTHER
TELECOMMUNICATION COMPANIES KNOWINGLY UNDER COLLECTED
AND UNDER REMITTED AMOUNTS DUE UNDER THE ACCESS LINE TAX
ORDINANCE IN VIOLATION OF THE CALIFORNIA FALSE CLAIMS ACT.
>> ALL RIGHT. I THINK THAT WE CAN TAKE THESE
ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S
GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER YES.
AT 230 IT IS NOW TIME FOR THE RECOGNIZE AND OF COMMENDATIONS
FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND I BELIEVE WE HAVE DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MANDELL DOMINANT YES COACH ADAM MAY I
HAVE YOU COME TO THE PODIUM? >> GOOD.
YES. GIVE HIM A BIG ROUND OF
APPLAUSE. GOOD AFTERNOON.
IT'S MY GREAT HONOR TODAY TO RECOGNIZE COACH KEVIN ADAMS, A
LIFELONG EDUCATOR, COACH AND MENTOR.
>> AFTER 43 YEARS OF DEDICATION TO HIS PLAYERS, COACH ADAM
RETIRED THIS YEAR. TODAY WE WISH TO CELEBRATE HIS
EXCEPTIONAL IMPACT ON GALIL HIGH SCHOOL AND SAN FRANCISCO
ATHLETICS COACH ADAM LETT GALI ALL FOOTBALL FROM 1981 TO 2008
WAS HEAD COACH FOR 15 SEASONS 110 SAN FRANCISCO TRIPLE EIGHT
CHAMPIONSHIPS AND FINISHED IT AS RUNNER UP SIX TIMES.
>> THIS LEAGUE IS THE CITY'S HIGHEST LEVEL OF HIGH SCHOOL
SPORTS FEATURING THE MOST ACCURATE AND DEDICATED ATHLETES
AND THEIR COACH ADAM'S LEADERSHIP GALEANO HAD THREE
UNDEFEATED SEASONS AND RANKED IN THE STATE'S TOP 80.
>> HIS TEAM REACHED IT THE TURKEY DAY CHAMPIONSHIPS 16
TIMES INCLUDING EIGHT STRAIGHT IN 1994.
HE WAS TWICE NAMED SAN FRANCISCO 888 COACH OF THE YEAR
AND HELPED LEAD THE NORTH TO SHOUT OUT WIN IN THE 1991 SHINE
GAME AT THE ROSE BOWL. >> BEYOND FOOTBALL HE ALSO LED
COLLEGE VARSITY BOYS BASKETBALL TEAMS TO CHAMPIONSHIP IN 1998
AND 2005 TO 1918 WAS RANKED THIRD IN THE BAY AREA AND HE
COACHED THE PLAYER OF THE YEAR. KENNY WAS DURING HIS CAREER.
>> HE ALSO COACHED AT TRACK AND FIELDS IN 1986.
>> HIS 4X4 HUNDRED REPLACED PLACED A FOURTH AT STATE
FINALS. THEIR RECORD TIMES IS STILL THE
FASTEST BY ANY SAN FRANCISCO HIGH SCHOOL TEAMS.
HIS FOUR BY 100 TEAM ALSO SET A SCHOOL RECORD AND PLACED A
SIXTH IN THE STATE. >> HIS HE IS ALSO COACHED AT
TWO NFL PLAYERS BOBBY SHAW AND THEN HE WAS AND HIS NEPHEW
JOEL MIXON WENT ON TO BECOME AN NFL STAR WITH COACH ADAMS
SUPPORT COACH ADAMS GUIDANCE EXTENDED BEYOND THE COURT.
>> HE MENTORS THREE STUDENT ATHLETIC ATHLETES WHO LATER
BECAME DOCTORS ADDITIONAL COACH .
>> ADAMS LEGACY IS RECOGNIZED IN SEVERAL LOCAL HALLS OF FAME.
>> AS A STUDENT ATHLETIC HIMSELF.
HE WAS AN NCAA DIVISION TWO NATIONAL FINALIST AND EARNED
HONOR AT BOTH SAN FRANCISCO STATE AND SKYLINE.
>> COACH ADAM STORY SHOWS THAT THE SUCCESS IS NOT JUST ABOUT
WINNING. >> IT'S ABOUT EFFORT.
IT'S ABOUT CHARACTER. >> IT'S ABOUT PERSEVERANCE.
THANK YOU, COACH ADAM FOR YOUR REMARKABLE CAREER AND YOUR
COMMITMENT TO UPLIFTING YOUR PLAYERS AND FOR INSPIRING
GENERATIONS OF ETHICS. >> THANK YOU.
CONGRATULATION. THANK YOU.
>> A THANK EVERYBODY FOR BEING HERE AGAIN.
THIS IS A GREAT HONOR TO BE RECOGNIZED AFTER LIKE YOU SAID,
43 YEARS GOES BY QUICK AGAIN WITHOUT GOOD STUDENTS GOOD
SUPPORT FROM THE ADMINISTRATION ALSO FROM THE CITY PERIOD.
JUST TO GIVE THE KIDS AN OPPORTUNITY THAT'S WHAT THAT'S
WHAT IT'S ALL ABOUT TO ME AGAIN, YOU KNOW, I'VE BEEN
LUCKY ENOUGH TO WIN SOME GAMES BUT I HAD TO HAVE SOME GOOD
PLAYERS ALSO. AND SOME GOOD COACHES THAT
HELPED ME GAIN SUPPORT FROM MY FAMILY ALSO, YOU KNOW IT'S A
STRONG BACKBOARD FROM MY FATHER, MOTHER AND MY
GRANDMOTHER AND YOU KNOW, ENCOURAGEMENT FROM MY SIBLINGS
AND ALSO SOME OF MY FRIENDS AND MY WIFE RIGHT HERE IVANA
WHO'S HERE AND RON KENNEDY AND NEIGHBORHOOD FRIEND.
AND JOE MAKES HIS DAD WHO'S RIGHT HERE AGAIN MY MY MY
SISTERS ALL THIS KID. SO AGAIN, I APPRECIATE THIS
HONOR AND I'LL NEVER FORGET IT .
AND I'M SURE THE KIDS WHO I TALKED TO HOPEFULLY SOMEDAY
THEY'LL BE UP HERE. >> THANK YOU
. ALL RIGHT.
IS NANCY ALFARO HERE? >> COME ON UP.
>> COLLEAGUES, TODAY WE HAVE ANOTHER BITTERSWEET
COMMENDATION. >> I'M PRESENTING A SPECIAL
COMMENDATION TO NANCY ALFARO WHO'S RETIRING FROM HER ROLE AS
DIRECTOR OF S.F. 311 AFTER MORE THAN 30 YEARS OF SERVICE TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO, NANCY FIRST JOINED
THE CITY IN 1992 AS A MANAGEMENT ASSISTANT.
SHE WORKED HER WAY UP THE RANKS AND BECAME OUR COUNTY CLERK
IN 1997. IN THAT ROLE SHE MODERNIZED
AND EXPANDED SERVICES TO THE PUBLIC, INCLUDING THE
INTRODUCTION OF ONLINE SYSTEMS FOR MARRIAGE LICENSES, CEREMONY
RESERVATIONS AND QUEUING TO MAKE IT EASIER TO ACCESS
SERVICES. SHE SUCCESSFULLY LOBBIED THE
STATE OF CALIFORNIA TO ACCEPT ELECTRONIC MARRIAGE LICENSES
WHICH ELIMINATED THE NEED FOR STAFF TO MANUALLY TYPE OUT EACH
LICENSE ON PAPER FORMS. SAN FRANCISCO BECAME THE FIRST
COUNTY IN THE STATE TO PRODUCE ELECTRONIC MARRIAGE LICENSES
WITH OTHER COUNTIES FOLLOWING OUR LEAD.
>> SHORTLY THEREAFTER IN 2004, NANCY HELPED MAKE HISTORY WHEN
SHE ISSUED THE CITY'S FIRST SAME SEX MARRIAGE LICENSES TO
ACTIVISTS JILL MARTIN AND PHYLLIS LYON.
UNDER DIRECTION FROM FORMER MAYOR GAVIN NEWSOM, NANCY'S
TEAM WORKED QUICKLY TO UPDATE MARRIAGE LICENSE FORMS TO
ACCOMMODATE SAME SEX COUPLES. BETWEEN FEBRUARY 12TH AND MARCH
11TH OF 2004, HER OFFICE ISSUED MORE THAN 4000 MARRIAGE
LICENSES TO SAME SEX COUPLES ALTHOUGH THE MARRIAGES WERE
LATER HALTED BY THE CALIFORNIA SUPREME COURT.
THE MONTH LONG WINTER OF LOVE BROUGHT NEW ENERGY TO THE FIGHT
FOR MARRIAGE EQUALITY. >> IN 2007, WHEN S.F. 311 WAS
CREATED, NANCY BECAME ITS DEPUTY DIRECTOR.
TWO YEARS LATER SHE TOOK OVER AS DIRECTOR OF THE CITY'S
CUSTOMER SERVICE CENTER WHICH CONNECTS THE PUBLIC TO CITY
DEPARTMENTS 24 HOURS A DAY, SEVEN DAYS A WEEK.
AS DIRECTOR SHE FOSTERED PARTNERSHIPS WITH DEPARTMENT
LEADERS TO MAKE IT EASIER FOR THE PUBLIC TO SUBMIT REQUESTS
AND IMPROVE THE CITY'S ABILITY TO RESOLVE REQUESTS
EFFECTIVELY. SHE IMPLEMENTED BUSINESS
PROCESS IMPROVEMENTS THAT LED TO FASTER SERVICE DELIVERY.
SHE ALSO CREATED NEW DATA AND REPORTING DASHBOARDS THAT
STRENGTHEN TRANSPARENT SEE AND ACCOUNTABILITY.
OVER THE PAST TWO DECADES, 3 IN 1 HAS EVOLVED SIGNIFICANTLY.
THE AGENCY ADDED ONLINE AND MOBILE APP SERVICES WHICH
ARE AVAILABLE IN SPANISH CHINESE AND FILIPINO AS WELL AS
ENGLISH. THE THREE ON ONE APP HAS
PROCESSED MORE THAN 4 MILLION SERVICE REQUESTS SINCE IT
LAUNCHED LAUNCHED. NANCY WE THANK YOU FOR MAKING
IT EASIER FOR SAN FRANCISCANS TO ACCESS CITY SERVICES.
YOU'VE HELPED TO MAKE OUR CITY A CLEANER, SAFER AND MORE
ACCESSIBLE PLACE TO LIVE, WORK AND RECREATE IN AND BEFORE I
INVITE YOU TO SAY A FEW WORDS, WE HAVE A NUMBER OF MY
COLLEAGUES WHO WANT TO TALK AND I BELIEVE OUR CITY
ADMINISTRATOR IS GOING TO HAVE A FEW THINGS TO SAY AS WELL.
>> SUPERVISOR CESAR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELL
THEN I WANT TO EXPRESS MY APPRECIATION TO THE BOARD
PRESIDENT FOR THAT FOR HONORING NANCY ALFARO.
I JUST WANT TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO YOU WHEN YOU WERE
COUNTY CLERK. THIS WAS, YOU KNOW, SOMETHING
THE MARRIAGE EQUALITY FIGHT WAS SOMETHING THAT WAS REALLY
PERSONAL TO ME. I WAS ONE OF ALONG WITH TERRY
STEWART, TWO OF THE MEMBERS OF THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE
EXECUTIVES, STAFF AND EVERYBODY WHO STOOD WITH THAT JUST MEANT
THE WORLD TO US. YOU COULD HAVE SAID NO.
AND I THINK IT'S APPROPRIATE IN THE HISTORY OF LGBTQ PLUS
RIGHTS THERE IS GOING TO BE A CASE WITH YOUR NAME ON IT
BECAUSE THEY SUED YOU. AND I ALWAYS THOUGHT THAT WAS
KIND OF GREAT BECAUSE BECAUSE YOU COULD HAVE SAID NO AND IT
REALLY DID MATTER AS IN THAT TIME WHEN WE WERE DOING
EVERYTHING WE COULD TO GET MARRIED, TO GET PEOPLE MARRIED
AND TO START A FIGHT THAT WOULD ACTUALLY MAKE HISTORY AND YOU
KNOW, CHANGE THE LAW. IT TOOK NINE YEARS BUT WE GOT
THERE AND YOU HAVE REALLY A SPECIAL PART IN THAT AND IT
MEANS A LOT TO ME. SO CONGRATULATIONS ON A
WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
SUPERVISORS ORDER. >> AND SO I WANT TO THANK YOU
FOR YOUR DECADES OF SERVICE TO THE CITY.
AND I APPRECIATE HEARING ABOUT ALL OF YOUR WORK BEFORE 311.
QUITE A REMARKABLE SET OF WORK THAT YOU'VE ENGAGED ON WITH THE
CITY. I APPRECIATE YOUR WORK ON 311
BECAUSE I THINK IT IS THE PROBABLY THE MOST COMMON WAY
THAT EVERYDAY CITIZENS ENGAGE WITH OUR CITY AND IS SOMETHING
THAT I WOULD SAY 99% OF THE TIME IT FEELS LIKE MAGIC TO
PEOPLE WHEN THEY USE IT AND IT'S A REALLY IMPORTANT
IMPORTANT WAY FOR US TO ENGAGE WITH EVERYONE AND IN PARTICULAR
IN THE LAST FEW MONTHS. YOU WERE WONDERFUL TO WORK WITH
AS WE TRIED TO KEEP THE THREE MOMENT OPEN API GOING AND IN
PARTICULAR TO MAKE SURE THAT WE CONTINUE TO SUPPORT SOLVE S.F..
THAT'S AN APP THAT PERSONALLY I USE MULTIPLE TIMES A DAY AND I
KNOW THOUSANDS OF OUR NEIGHBORS DO AS WELL SO THANK YOU FOR ALL
OF YOUR SERVICE AND ALL OF YOUR WORK TO IMPROVE SAN FRANCISCO
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT
MANDELL FOR DOING THIS COMMENDATION AND THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE FOR OUR CITY.
I HAVE TO JUST SHARE THAT LIKE PERSONALLY HOW MUCH YOU'VE
MEANT TO ME. I MET YOU WHEN I WAS WORKING
FOR GAVIN NEWSOM WHEN HE WAS MAYOR AND WE WERE A HANDFUL
AND I MEAN A HANDFUL OF LATINAS WORKING IN GOVERNMENT AT THE
TIME. AND I HAVE SEEN YOU AT YOUR
LEADERSHIP, YOUR VISIBILITY FOR THE REST OF US IN THAT POSITION
OF POWER AND EVERYTHING THAT YOU'VE DONE SO COMPETENTLY
AND SO WONDERFULLY YOU ARE JUST IT'S JUST BEEN AN HONOR TO WORK
WITH YOU AND THE DIFFERENT THINGS THAT YOU'VE DONE
AND AGAIN TO THANK YOU AS FROM ONE LATINA TO ANOTHER FOR YOUR
VISIBILITY, YOUR REPRESENTATION AND THE WAY THAT YOU HAVE
CARRIED YOURSELF IN THIS POSITION AND WHAT YOU'VE MEANT
FOR THE REST OF US. SO THANK YOU, NANCY.
>> I'M SORRY THAT YOU'RE LEAVING BUT I APPRECIATE YOU
AND ADMIRE YOU. AND YEAH, YOU'RE GOING TO LIVE
ON IN OUR HISTORY AND THE HISTORY OF THIS COUNTRY
AND THAT MAKES ME SO, SO PROUD .
>> AND NOW CITY ADMINISTRATOR CARMEN CHIU.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MIDDLEMAN AND OF COURSE THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR ALLOWING US TO HONOR A REALLY A
TRUE PUBLIC SERVANT HERE. NANCY IS JOINED BY HER FAMILY
SO I WONDER IF THEY WOULD JUST STAND FOR A MINUTE SO WE CAN
SEE THEM AND RECOGNIZE THEM. LET'S GIVE THEM A BIG ROUND OF
APPLAUSE. >> I THINK AS AS MANY OF YOU
HAVE ALREADY ARTICULATED AND PRESIDENT AND YOU ALREADY
ARTICULATED SO MANY OF NANCY'S ACCOMPLISHMENTS, THERE IS SO
MUCH THAT WE WILL MISS ABOUT NANCY AND MYSELF INCLUDED.
IT IS OFTEN HARD TO REPLACE SOMEONE WHO IS SO EXCELLENT
AND SO AMAZING TO WORK WITH AND SO WE'RE GOING TO HAVE
REALLY TOUGH SHOES TO FILL. NANCY, WITH YOUR DEPARTURE I
REMEMBER WHEN SHE HAD ACTUALLY SET UP THE APPOINTMENT TO MEET
WITH ME TO LET ME KNOW THAT SHE WAS LEAVING OR RETIRING AND I'M
LIKE OH NO, I KNOW WHAT THIS IS.
>> WHENEVER SOMEONE GIVES ME AN APPOINTMENT AND IT'S NOT ONE OF
THE THINGS THAT I'M EXPECTING I KNOW IT'S GOT TO BE ABOUT THIS
AND SO IN FACT IT WAS AND I WILL SAY THAT AS SOMEONE WHO
HAS SEEN NANCY WORK AT THE COUNTY CLERK'S OFFICE BUT NOT
ONLY THAT AND 311 IN MY LATEST CAPACITY HERE SHE IS SOMEONE
WHO HAS ALWAYS BEEN A TRUE CHAMPION OF PUBLIC SERVICE
AND REALLY ABOUT WHAT IT MEANS TO PROVIDE EXCELLENT SERVICE TO
ANYONE WHO COMES THROUGH THE DOOR.
AND I THINK THAT'S WHAT SHE'S TRIED TO DO BOTH AT THE COUNTY
CLERK'S OFFICE AND ALSO 311 REGARDLESS OF WHERE YOU COME
FROM, WHAT YOUR LANGUAGE CAPACITY IS, SHE UNDERSTANDS AT
THAT FIRST INTERACTION THAT THE PUBLIC HAS WITH US WILL SET AN
EXAMPLE FOR HOW THEY THINK ABOUT THEIR GOVERNMENT AND HOW
IT IS THAT WE'RE RESPONSIVE. SO JUST HAVING SOMEONE WHO IS
CONSTANTLY AWARE OF THAT IMPORTANCE, SOMEONE WHO IS
CONSTANTLY INNOVATING AND NEVER REALLY CONTENT TO SAY HOW IT IS
IS HOW IT SHOULD BE BUT ALWAYS TRYING TO FIGURE OUT THE NEXT
THING TO DO TO IMPROVE SERVICE, THE NEXT KIND OF THING TO BUILD
ON IN ORDER TO MAKE IT MORE CONVENIENT FOR WORKERS OR FOR
PEOPLE TO ACCESS GOVERNMENT SERVICES IS A TRUE TRUE TRUE
TREASURE. I THINK AS YOU KNOW SO MANY OF
THE PEOPLE IN YOUR CITY GOVERNMENT WORK INCREDIBLY HARD
AND THEY ARE THE UNSUNG HEROES TO THE WORK THAT IS HERE
AND NANCY IS TRULY ONE OF THOSE CHAMPIONS.
BUT ABOVE AND BEYOND THAT, THE THING THAT MOST PEOPLE DON'T
SEE IS JUST HOW MUCH SHE TRULY LOVES AND CHERISHES HER
EMPLOYEES AND THE PEOPLE THAT WORK FOR HER.
SHE IS SOMEONE WHO IS ROUTINELY HAVING FUN COMMITTEE PARTIES
WHERE SHE IS LIKE MAKING SURE TO RECOGNIZE THE STAFF
AND THEIR GREAT WORK AND I THINK THAT'S IMPORTANT TO
CELEBRATE EACH OTHER AND TO CELEBRATE THE GREAT WORK THAT
THEY'RE DOING. SO NANCY, YOU'RE NOT GOING TO
ONLY BE MISSED BECAUSE OF THE WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE TO
MODERNIZE AND MOVE OUR GOVERNMENT FORWARD AND FOR ALL
OF THE INNOVATION AND AND WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE, WE'RE GOING
TO MISS YOU FOR YOUR PARTNERSHIP.
WE'RE GOING TO MISS THE FACT THAT WE'RE LOSING A REALLY
GREAT PERSON AMONGST US AS A COLLEAGUE, SOMEONE WHO HAS
HUMANITY AND UNDERSTANDING OF WHAT'S NECESSARY TO SERVE
PEOPLE. BUT BECAUSE ALL OF YOUR
EMPLOYEES AND ALL OF US WILL JUST MISS WORKING WITH YOU AS A
HUMAN BEING YOU'RE JUST A REALLY GREAT PERSON AND SO AT
THE END OF THE DAY TO ME THAT IS THE THING THAT IS MOST
IMPORTANT IS HOW YOU LIVE YOUR LIFE AND HOW YOU TREAT OTHERS
AND YOU DO THAT WITH DIGNITY AND WE WILL MISS THAT.
>> SO NANCY, TO YOUR 30 YEARS, THANK YOU SO, SO, SO VERY MUCH.
WE COULDN'T BE HERE WITHOUT ALL OF YOUR GREAT WORK.
>> CONGRATULATIONS. >> I BEING IN THE SPOTLIGHT IS
NOT ONE OF THE THINGS I LIKE. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS
INCREDIBLE HONOR. I'M IT'S JUST I HAVE SO MUCH
HONOR RESPECT FOR EVERYTHING THAT YOU DO.
I AM JUST SO APPRECIATIVE OF THE SUPPORT AND OPPORTUNITIES
THAT I HAVE BEEN GIVEN THROUGHOUT MY CAREER.
I HAVE GAINED SO MUCH KNOWLEDGE, INSPIRATION FROM SO
MANY CITY LEADERS JUST LIKE OUR CITY ADMINISTRATOR CARMEN TO
OUR DEPUTY CITY ADMINISTRATOR JENNIFER JOHNSON WHO WERE
ALWAYS STANDING BY MY SIDE SUPPORTING EVERY CRAZY IDEA I
MIGHT BRING UP. BUT THEY TRUSTED MY JUDGMENT
AND APPRECIATED ANYTHING THAT I BROUGHT THAT WAS INNOVATIVE
AND ALWAYS WITH THE PUBLIC'S INTERESTS IN MIND.
AS SHE SAID, THAT'S REALLY IMPORTANT TO ME.
>> BUT AS I REFLECT ON MY ACCOMPLISHMENTS I REMEMBER
STARTING AS A YOUNG MANAGEMENT ASSISTANT HAVING NO CLUE WHAT
THE NEXT 30 YEARS WERE GOING TO COME UP AND BE PART OF ME.
>> BUT I AM REALLY FORTUNATE TO HAVE HAD MANAGERS THAT REALLY
BELIEVED IN ME THAT SAW MY POTENTIAL, THAT TAUGHT ME THAT
ENCOURAGED ME TO APPLY FOR HIGHER POSITIONS AND THAT LED
ME TO HAVE CONFIDENCE IN MYSELF AND YOU KNOW, BUILD TWO
DEPARTMENTS, TWO BRAND NEW DEPARTMENTS BECAUSE THE COUNTY
CLERK HAD SEPARATED FROM THE RECORDER'S OFFICE AND THEN 311
WHO WAS JUST WIRES HANGING OFF OF THE WALL WHEN I FIRST CAME
TO 311. SO IT'S PRETTY EXCITING AND NOT
MANY PEOPLE HAVE THAT OPPORTUNITY AS WELL AS THE
HISTORY THAT WAS MADE WITH THE SAME SEX MARRIAGES.
>> SO I'M VERY PROUD OF ALL OF THAT AND I ALWAYS KEEP THAT
IN MIND AS I STAND HERE NOW AS DIRECTOR OF 311.
BUT I COULDN'T HAVE ACCOMPLISHED THIS WITHOUT MY
EMPLOYEES. >> YOU KNOW, THEY ARE REALLY
WHO MAKE SUCCESS OUT OF YOUR LEADERS.
>> RIGHT. AND I MEAN THE EMPLOYEES OF THE
COUNTY CLERKS, THE VOLUNTEERS AT THE COUNTY CLERKS ARE
AMAZING INDIVIDUALS. ALL THE COLLEAGUES FROM THE ALL
THE VARIOUS CITY DEPARTMENTS WITHOUT THEIR SUPPORT 311 WOULD
NOT EXIST AND WE WOULDN'T HAVE BEEN ABLE TO ANSWER QUESTIONS
TO THE PUBLIC AND OF COURSE ALL OF THE 311 STUFF I MEAN THEY
MEAN THE WORLD TO ME. >> THEY'RE PASSIONATE,
DEDICATED, HARDWORKING INDIVIDUALS WHO REALLY HAVE
TRULY HAVE A PASSION FOR CUSTOMER SERVICE AND THEY ARE
DOING EVERYTHING THEY WANT BECAUSE THEY WANT IT BETTER FOR
THE PUBLIC. THEY I ALWAYS SAY IT'S A
SPECIAL TYPE OF INDIVIDUAL THAT ACCEPTS THESE TYPE OF JOBS
BECAUSE IT'S NOT FOR EVERYONE AND WE UNDERSTAND THAT.
BUT WE DO HIRE SOME OF THE BEST PEOPLE AND THEY REALLY CARE
ABOUT THE PEOPLE THAT ARE ON THE OTHER LINE ON THE PHONE OR
ON THE COUNTER AND THAT'S REALLY IMPORTANT AND THEY'RE
GOING TO HAVE A SPECIAL PLACE IN MY HEART FOR SURE.
>> NATURALLY I WANT TO THANK MY FAMILY.
>> RIGHT. MY PARENTS WERE GREAT ROLE
MODELS. MY MOM IS RIGHT NOW WATCHING I
THINK THE BOARD MEETING ON THE COMPUTER AND UNFORTUNATELY MY
DAD COULDN'T BE HERE ANYMORE TO SEE ME BUT I KNOW HE WOULD BE
SO SO PROUD. >> THEY REALLY INSTILLED GREAT
VALUES IN ALL OF US. >> THEY TOLD US TO WORK HARD,
HAVE GOOD WORK ETHIC, YOU KNOW, AND THAT'S WHAT I THINK ALLOWED
ME TO GET TO WHERE I AM TODAY. >> THAT WAS REALLY IMPORTANT
AND OF COURSE I HAD TO KEEP THIS A LITTLE BIT LOW KEY
BECAUSE OTHERWISE I WOULD PROBABLY HAVE 20 FAMILY MEMBERS
A LATINA YOU KNOW EVERY SECOND COUSIN AND EVERY AUNT IS
IMMEDIATE FAMILY. >> SO BUT I DO HAVE SOME
SPECIAL PEOPLE HERE. >> MY HUSBAND OF COURSE WHO HAS
BEEN LIKE ONE OF MY BIGGEST SUPPORTERS, YOU KNOW, EVEN WHEN
HE KNEW THAT SOME OF THESE JOBS WERE GOING TO REQUIRE WORKING
REALLY LATE WORKING WEEKENDS NO MATTER WHAT, WE HAD YOUNG
CHILDREN. HE WAS LIKE I KNOW YOU CAN DO
THIS. TAKE THE OPPORTUNITY, DON'T LET
THIS GO BY. SO HE WAS ALWAYS THERE FOR ME
SO THANK YOU HARD HERE I HAVE YOU KNOW MY OLDER SON, MY
SISTER, MY BROTHER, MY NIECE YOU KNOW, HERE WITH THEIR
FAMILY SUPPORTING ME BECAUSE I HAVE ALWAYS HAD THAT LOVE
AND SUPPORT FROM THEM AND THAT'S BEEN VERY, VERY
IMPORTANT TO ME AND TO MY SUCCESS.
>> AND JUST LASTLY, I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT IT'S JUST BEEN A
GREAT HONOR TO HAVE THIS RECOGNITION WORKING FOR THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO HAS TRULY BEEN JUST
AMAZING. >> I'VE HAD JUST A WONDERFUL
TIME. IT DOES GO QUICK.
I DON'T EVEN FEEL LIKE IT'S BEEN OVER 30 YEARS BUT MY AGE
SAYS OTHERWISE SO I LEAVE WITH MY HEAD HELD HIGH AND VERY
PROUD OF WHAT I'VE BEEN ABLE TO ACCOMPLISH IN THESE LAST 30
YEARS. >> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
OH OH OH BUT THEY HAVE TO DO THIS TOGETHER OR MAYBE A
PICTURE WITH THE BOARD CHAIR WHEN I'M GOING FROM THE HOUSE
THAT YOU'RE IN VIDEO. OKAY.
YOU KNOW WELL SO I JUST THINK WITH THAT I THINK YOU GET TO
MAKE LIKE ALL RIGHT PEOPLE BACK TO WORK.
MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 21 AND 22 TOGETHER
ITEMS 21 AND 22 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A
REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY SEPTEMBER 8TH AND ARE TWO
MOTIONS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED TO APPROVE PRESIDENT RAFAEL
MENDELSSOHN'S TWO NOMINATION APPOINTMENTS AS COMMITTEE
REPORTS. ACTUALLY WE ARE STRIKING ONE
WORD IN EACH MOTION AND THAT IS THE WORD REJECTING.
SO WE HAVE NEW TITLES THESE ARE APPOINTMENTS TO THE SAN
FRANCISCO DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION AND ECONOMIC
RECOVERY FINANCING DISTRICT BOARD OF DIRECTORS FOR ITEM 21.
THIS MOTION APPROVES THE APPOINTMENT OF ANTONIO
TOLENTINO TERM ENDING JULY 22ND 2027 AND FOR ITEM 22 THIS
MOTION APPROVES KRISTIN WONG TERM ENDING JULY 22ND 2020 NINE
OKAY I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MOTIONS ARE APPROVED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO
TO ROLL CALL TO PROFESSOR MAHMOOD YOUR FIRST UP TO
INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM CALLING
ALL BOOKWORMS OXFORD COMMA DEBATERS AND READING ESCAPISTS
BECAUSE AS THE SON OF A FORMER LIBRARIAN I AM PROUDLY
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING SEPTEMBER AS
LIBRARY CARD SIGN-UP MONTH IN SAN FRANCISCO THIS
RESOLUTION UPLIFTS THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY SYSTEM
THE BEST IN THE NATION. JUST ASK OUR CITY LIBRARIAN
MICHAEL LAMBERT AND REMINDS US OF THE EXTRAORDINARY RESOURCES
AVAILABLE TO EVERY RESIDENT WITH JUST A FREE LIBRARY CARD.
>> OUR CITY HAS 27 NEIGHBORHOOD BRANCHES PLUS THE MAIN LIBRARY
ENSURING THAT EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD HAS ACCESS TO
KNOWLEDGE, CULTURE AND COMMUNITY.
>> A LIBRARY CARD PROVIDES ACCESS TO MILLIONS OF EBOOKS
AND AUDIO BOOKS, RESEARCH TOOLS AND KANOPY A WORLD CLASS
STREAMING SERVICE WITH AWARD WINNING FILMS AND DOCUMENTARIES
THROUGH DISCOVERY AND GO FAMILIES CAN ALSO ACCESS FREE
PASSES TO MUSEUMS AND CULTURAL INSTITUTIONS ACROSS THE BAY
AREA. >> THE LIBRARY IS FAR MORE THAN
BOOKS AND IT'S FREE HOMEWORK HELP DIGITAL LITERACY TRAINING,
SMALL BUSINESS RESOURCES AND A CIVIC AND A SAFE CIVIC SPACE
WHERE ALL SAN FRANCISCANS CAN GATHER AND LEARN FLAGSHIP
PROGRAMS LIKE NATIVE IDEAS SHOWCASE THE LIBRARY'S ROLE AS
A HUB FOR CULTURE DIALOG AND CIVIC ENGAGEMENT AND SIMPLY
FUN. >> NOW AT THE NATIONAL LEVEL
LIBRARIES WE HAVE TO ACKNOWLEDGE ARE UNDER ATTACK.
>> FEDERAL FUNDING FOR THE INSTITUTE OF MUSEUM AND LIBRARY
SERVICES RESPONSIBLE FOR HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS IN LIBRARY
GRANTS FACE ELIMINATION AND STATES LIKE OHIO AND OREGON
ARE ALREADY CUTTING BACK ON LOCAL FUNDING.
THESE CUTS ARE ALREADY DISRUPTING INTER LIBRARY LOANS,
DIGITAL ACCESS AND PROGRAMING ACCESS ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
>> IN SOME COMMUNITIES RESIDENTS ARE LOSING ACCESS TO
THE VERY SERVICES THAT CONNECT THEM TO THE EDUCATION
AND OPPORTUNITY THEY NEED. >> AGAINST THIS BACKDROP IT IS
IMPORTANT NOW MORE THAN EVER THAT SAN FRANCISCO CONTINUES TO
CHAMPION OUR TOP TIER LIBRARY SYSTEM AS A MODEL OF EQUITY
DIVERSITY AND INCLUSION AND MOST IMPORTANTLY FREEDOM OF
ACCESS TO INFORMATION. I THANK ALL MY CO SPONSORS
RANDLEMAN MELGAR AND GARCIA AND CHEN AND ALL MY COLLEAGUES
TO JOIN US IN ENCOURAGING RESIDENTS FROM LIFELONG SAN
FRANCISCANS TO NEWCOMERS TO SIGN UP FOR A FREE LIBRARY CARD
THIS MONTH. THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUPERVISOR MELGAR EXCUSE ME.
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN APOLOGIES, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> I DO HAVE A FEW ITEMS TODAY
. ONE IS COLLEAGUES I AM
INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO NEARLY SEVEN YEARS AFTER IT WAS
IMPOSED OR APPROVE MOVED TO REPEAL OUR NEVER YET IMPOSED
CANNABIS BUSINESS TAX AGAIN BACK IN NOVEMBER OF 2018 VOTERS
VOTED ON THIS MEASURE IN 2019. AT THIS HOUR OUR BOARD NOT THIS
BOARD BUT OUR BOARD OF SUPERVISORS I THINK CORRECTLY
DECIDED TO DELAY THE IMPOSITION OF THE TAX FOR A YEAR IN 2021
WE APPROVED ANOTHER YEARLONG DELAY AND IN 2022 WE APPROVED A
THREE YEAR DELAY AND I THINK IN EACH OF THESE CASES WE HAVE
RECOGNIZED THAT OUR LEGAL CANNABIS INDUSTRY FACES UNIQUE
CHALLENGES FROM FEDERAL AND STATE REGULATION AND THAT
THEY ARE COMPETING AGAINST A DOMINANT ILLICIT MARKET IN THAT
ENVIRONMENT WE HAVE BEEN RELUCTANT TO FURTHER BURDEN THE
LEGAL MARKET AS A FEDERALLY CLASSIFIED SCHEDULE ONE
CONTROLLED SUBSTANCE CANNABIS BUSINESSES CANNOT DEDUCT
ORDINARY EXPENSES FROM THEIR REVENUE.
>> THIS CREATES A TAX BURDEN THAT LEADS TO INCREASED COSTS
AND LIABILITIES FOR INDIVIDUAL BUSINESSES.
IT ALSO MEANS THAT LEGAL CANNABIS BUSINESSES CANNOT
ACCESS CONVENTIONAL BANKING SYSTEMS AND MUST HAVE INCREASED
SECURITY AND OVERHEAD TO SECURE THEIR CASH RUN BUSINESSES
BURGERS OFTEN BURGLARS OFTEN TARGET CANNABIS BUSINESSES
KNOWING THAT THEY KEEP CASH ON HAND.
OUR LEGAL CANNABIS BUSINESSES ARE SUBJECT TO HIGH STATE TAXES
WHICH HAVE RECENTLY AND INEXPLICABLY TO MY MIND
GONE UP AND SO I KNOW WE ARE NOT ALL OF ONE MIND ABOUT THIS
BUT I DO THINK IT IS WORTH HAVING THE CONVERSATION IF WE
DO NOT HAVE THE CONVERSATION. THIS TAX KICKS IN NEXT YEAR
WHICH I THINK WOULD BE A BIG MISTAKE AND A AND VERY NEGATIVE
FOR OUR EFFORTS TO TO SUPPORT THE LEGAL INDUSTRY AND GET RID
OF THE ILLEGAL CANNABIS INDUSTRY.
I DO WANT TO THANK ON HON. MY OFFICE FOR HIS WORK ON THIS
LEGISLATION AND I WANT TO THANK CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISOR DORST
SUPERVISOR SOARES SUPERVISORS DORSI SAUTTER AND MAHMOOD THANK
YOU COLLEAGUES FOR THAT. >> I'M ALSO ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF PETER KANE WHO
DIED ON JULY 15TH AFTER TEN YEARS OF HEALTH CHALLENGES
RELATED TO TYPE ONE DIABETES AND HIV WITH WHICH HE HAD LIVED
FOR DECADES. PETER WAS BORN IN LONDON,
ENGLAND AND EMIGRATED TO THE UNITED STATES ON THE SS FRANCE
WITH HIS PARENTS IN MAY OF 1971 HIS FAMILY SETTLED IN SOUTHERN
CALIFORNIA WHERE HE WENT TO HIGH SCHOOL AND ATTENDED PIERCE
COLLEGE. IN 1977 HE TRANSFERRED TO SAN
FRANCISCO STATE AFTER GRADUATING IN 1979, PETER BEGAN
HIS CAREER IN RETAIL. HE WORKED AT THE GAP AND THEN
AT NEW YORK MAN IN THE CASTRO. IT WAS THERE THAT HE WORKED
WITH BOB FARINA AND LEARNED HOW TO RUN A SMALL RETAIL BUSINESS.
IN 1989 PETER OPENED HIS OWN RETAIL STORE IN THE CASTRO
WHICH HE NAMED CITIZEN. HE AND BOB ALSO STARTED A SIDE
BUSINESS SOURCING FABRIC AND FINISHED SHIRTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO TO SELL AT CITIZEN. TWO YEARS LATER PETER EXPANDED
HIS BUSINESS AND OPENED A SECOND STORE IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD BODY. BY 2011 THE STORES WERE LOCATED
ACROSS THE STREET FROM EACH OTHER ON CASTRO STREET.
EACH WAS AN ICONIC FASHION DESTINATION FOR LOCALS
AND TOURISTS. IN 2015 PETER WON A BEST
DISPLAY BEST WINDOW DISPLAY AWARD FROM BRITISH FASHION
DESIGNER BEN SHERMAN. HE WAS AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE
CASTRO COMMUNITY AND A LONG TIME MEMBER AND BOARD MEMBER OF
THE CASTRO MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION.
HIS ADVOCACY LED TO THE HANGING OF THE FLOWER PLANTERS IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD. IN 2018 THE OFFICE OF SMALL
BUSINESS HONORED PETER FOR HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO SAN FRANCISCO
AND POSTED THAT PETER EXEMPLIFIED THE BEST OF SAN
FRANCISCO SMALL BUSINESS AND MADE FAT AND MADE THE
CASTRO A FASHION SHOPPING DESTINATION.
BESIDES HIS KEY FOR FASHION BESIDES HIS KEEN EYE FOR
FASHION AND TALENT FOR KEEPING TRACK OF THE LATEST TRENDS,
PETER WAS KNOWN FOR HIS LOVE OF THEATER.
HE OFTEN TRAVELED TO NEW YORK AND LONDON TO SEE THE LATEST
SHOWS AND MUSICAL PERFORMANCES AND HAD AN EXTENSIVE EXTENSIVE
COLLECTION OF VINYL AND CD'S THAT HE WOULD DISPLAY IN HIS
STORE WINDOWS. PETER SURVIVED BY HIS MOTHER
VALERIE, HIS BROTHER ANDY NEPHEWS BRAD AND NICK, HIS
FORMER PARTNER AND BEST FRIEND OF 45 YEARS JEFF LEITER AND HIS
ADOPTED SON NICO PETRY. MATT MITCHELL.
REST IN PEACE. PETER CAIN MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A
BLESSING. AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MENDELSOHN MR. PRESIDENT.
NEXT UP IS SUPERVISOR MELGAR. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISORS. >> HARDER.
YES. COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A HEARING REQUEST ON THE PERFORMANCE OF THE
CITY'S MAIN DISASTER TRAINING PROGRAM.
THE NEIGHBORHOOD EMERGENCY RESPONSE TEAM.
MORE COMMONLY KNOWN AS INERT HAS BEEN AROUND SINCE 1990
AND HAS TRAINED THOUSANDS OF RESIDENTS TO PREPARE FOR MAJOR
EVENTS LIKE EARTHQUAKE FIRE AND OTHER DISASTERS.
BETWEEN THE TERRIBLE SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA FIRES AND THE RECENT
TSUNAMI SCARE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO THERE IS MORE
INTEREST THAN EVER IN GETTING OUR CITY AND CITIZENS READY TO
CARE FOR THEMSELVES AND ONE ANOTHER IN CASE OF EMERGENCY.
AND SEPTEMBER HAPPENS TO BE A NATURAL PREPAREDNESS MONTH
WHICH FURTHER UNDERSCORES THE NEED TO BE READY.
NERD IS A FANTASTIC PROGRAM RUN THROUGH THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
DEPARTMENT. I COMPLETED INERT TRAINING
MYSELF SOME SEVEN YEARS AGO AND FOUND IT TO BE EYE OPENING
AND IMPORTANT. I'M HOPING I'M HOPING THAT OUR
HEARING WILL ANSWER QUESTIONS SUCH AS HOW DO OUR 12,000
ACTIVE NERD GRADUATES PREPARE US IN COMPARISON TO OTHER
CITIES? AND JUST AS WE HAVE A COURSE
FOR SPANISH SPEAKING RESIDENTS, CAN WE HAVE A SIMILAR APPROACH
FOR CANTONESE SPEAKING RESIDENTS?
CAN WE EMBED NURSE TRAINING AND OTHER EDUCATIONAL SETTINGS
LIKE HIGH SCHOOLS? THESE ARE SOME OF THE QUESTIONS
WE HOPE TO ADDRESS SO I LOOK FORWARD TO OUR HEARING TO MAKE
SURE THAT WE'RE DOING EVERYTHING POSSIBLE AS A CITY
TO PREPARE FOR EMERGENCIES. >> AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SORTER SUPERVISOR
CHERYL SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN.
SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN. YES, COLLEAGUE.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM EXCITED
TO INTRODUCE OUR RESIDENTIAL TENANT PROTECTIONS ORDINANCE.
>> THIS ORDINANCE OFFERS PROACTIVE STRATEGY TO EXPAND
THE RIGHTS OF TENANTS WHO FACE DISPLACEMENT WHEN A DEVELOPER
OR LANDLORD PURSUES THE DEMOLITION OF A TENANT OCCUPIED
A PROPERTY IN ORDER TO BUILD NEW HOUSING.
>> THIS ORDINANCE APPLIES CITYWIDE AND CREATES A SET OF
NEW POLICIES AND SYSTEM OF ENFORCEMENT.
>> IT COMES AT A CUTOFF. IT COMES AT A CRUCIAL JUNCTURE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> DEVELOPERS NOW HAVE A HOST
OF NEW TOOLS AND INCENTIVES TO ADVANCE PROJECTS FROM DENSITY
BONUSES, STREAMLINING PROVISIONS AND INCREASING
DEVELOPMENT POTENTIAL TO PROPOSED REZONING.
NOT TO MENTION STATE LAWS WHICH ENABLE THE DEMOLITIONS OF
EXISTING RENT CONTROLLED IT AND TENANT OCCUPIED HOUSING.
AT RECENT HEARINGS OF THE LAND USE COMMITTEE AND THE PLANNING
COMMISSION WE HAVE SEEN AN OUTPOURING OF COMMUNITY VOICES
HUMANIZING THE STRUGGLE OF EVERYDAY SAN FRANCISCANS WHO
FEAR DISPLACEMENT. >> THEY INCLUDE ELDERLY TENANTS
WHO ARE RELYING ON THEIR SUPPORT NETWORKS IN EXISTING
RENT CONTROL HOUSING SUCH AS GROCERIES, STORES, DOCTORS,
TRANSIT AND NEIGHBORS WHO SUPPORT THEM AND ARE TERRIFIED
OF THE DISRUPTION TO THIS NETWORK IF THEY ARE DISPLACED
FROM THEIR HOME. WHEN LANDLORDS CHOOSE TO
REDEVELOP ALL THE REAL FEARS OF TENANTS WHO ARE FORCED TO
ABSORB UNMANAGEABLE RENT INCREASE ON A PRIVATE MARKET
WHEN THEIR LANDLORD CHOOSE TO REDEVELOP THEIR BUILDINGS
AND DISPLACE TENANTS THROUGH NO FAULT OF THEIR OWN.
>> THIS LEGISLATION'S PROVIDES SOLUTIONS TO HELP FILL THE GAPS
IN POLICY, ENFORCEMENT AND ACCOUNTABILITY.
>> IT ESTABLISHED COMMON SENSE RULES FOR DEVELOPERS AND COMMON
SENSE PROTECTIONS FOR RESIDENTIAL TENANTS.
>> THIS LEGISLATION ESTABLISHES A FEW BULLET POINTS ONE
EXTENSIVE TENANT NOTIFICATION THAT IS LINGUISTICALLY
ASSESSABLE TO ALL STEPS OF ENTITLEMENT FROM APPLICATION
SUBMITTAL TO A PERMIT APPROVAL. SECOND RELOCATION ASSISTANCE
FOR ALL DISPLACED TENANTS WITH ADDITIONAL ASSISTANCE TO LOW
LOWER INCOME TENANTS, A RELOCATION PLAN AND SPECIALISTS
TO FACILITATE TO FACILITATE THE IMPLEMENTATION OF REQUIRED
PROTECTIONS. >> A RIGHT FOR TENANTS TO
REMAIN IN THEIR HOMES FOR AT LEAST SIX MONTHS WITH TIME
SPECIFIC NOTIFICATION. A RIGHT TO RETURN A PAYROLL
RENTAL RATE IF DEMOLITION DOES NOT POLICY AND UNITS ARE
RETURNED TO THE RENTAL MARKETS. >> A RIGHT OF FIRST REFUSAL.
>> A RIGHT OF FIRST REFUSAL FOR LOWER INCOME TENANTS TO MOVE
INTO A NEWLY DEVELOPED DEVELOPED AT UNITS APPEARING
PAY RENT OR AN AFFORDABLE RENT WHICH IS WHICHEVER IS LOWER.
>> REPLACEMENT OF ALL PROTECTED UNITS IN BUILDINGS THAT WILL BE
DEMOLISHED WITH A COMBINATION OF RENT CONTROL AND BELOW
MARKET RATE UNITS. >> ADDITIONAL TOOLS FOR TENANTS
TO STOP TENANT HARASSMENT BEFORE THEY ARE DISPLACED
AND BEFORE LANDLORD HAVE TO COMPLYING WITH THE PROVISIONS
OF THIS ORDINANCE. >> THIS LEGISLATION IS INFORMED
BY ON THE GROUND EXPERTISE OF TENANTS AND COUNSELORS LAWYERS
AND ADVOCATES WHO HAVE TO TAKE PART IN A CALL.
VERY WARY PANIC CALLS FROM COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHEN THEY ARE
FACED WITH EVICTIONS AND HOUSING INSECURITY.
I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE LEADERSHIP AFTER RACE
AND EQUITY IN ALL PLANNING COALITIONS AND THE SAN
FRANCISCO ANTI DISPLACEMENT COALITION IN HELPING TO CRAFT
THIS ORDINANCE. I WANT TO ALSO THANK MY
LEGISLATIVE AIDE CHARLIE SHIMKUS FOR COORDINATING SUCH
COLLABORATIVE AND PARTICIPATORY PROCESS TO DEVELOP THIS
LEGISLATION. I ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE
PARTNERSHIP EXPERTISE AND COLLABORATIONS FROM
PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO RENT BOUGHT AND CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE. >> I KNOW THAT THIS IS ALSO AN
ISSUES OUR MAYOR CARES A LOT AND THAT OUR MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD ALSO HAVE STATED REPEATEDLY ON RECORD THAT WE
ARE COMMITTED TO DEFENDING TENANTS IN THIS CITY.
SO WITH THAT I WANT TO THANK MY CO-SPONSORSHIP SUPERVISOR
FIELDER WALTON CHAN AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WORK WITH MY REST WITH THE REST OF MY
COLLEAGUES AND GET YOUR SUPPORT.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I ASK THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS IN REMEMBRANCE OF JOHN BURTON, A TRUE SON OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND A ONE ONCE IN A GENERATION POLITICAL LEADER
WHOSE INFLUENCE SPANNED SIX DECADES AND WHOSE LEGACY WILL
ENDURE FOR MANY DECADES MORE. JOHN BURTON WAS A PROUDLY
LIBERAL, FIERCELY OUTSPOKEN AND DEEPLY COMPASSIONATE
LAWMAKER AND LEADER. HE BELIEVED THAT THE MOST
IMPORTANT DUTY OF GOVERNMENT WAS TO HELP THOSE LEAST ABLE TO
HELP THEMSELVES. THAT SIMPLE CONVICTION GUIDED A
LIFETIME OF PUBLIC SERVICE. TOGETHER WITH HIS BROTHER
PHILIP BURTON, HIS SISTER IN LAW SALA BURTON AND HIS
LIFELONG FRIEND AND POLITICAL ALLY WILLIE BROWN, JOHN HELPED
TO BUILD A POLITICAL ORGANIZATION THAT NOT ONLY
RESHAPED SAN FRANCISCO BUT ALSO GAVE RISE TO SOME OF THE MOST
CONSEQUENTIAL LEADERS IN STATE AND NATIONAL POLITICS NANCY
PELOSI, BARBARA BOXER, KAMALA HARRIS AND GAVIN NEWSOM AMONG
THEM. >> AS A MEMBER OF THE U.S.
CONGRESS CALIFORNIA STATE ASSEMBLY AND AS CALIFORNIA
STATE SENATE PRESIDENT PRO TEMPORE JOHN BURTON WAS A
LEGISLATIVE GIANT. HE AUTHORED AND FOUGHT FOR
LANDMARK MEASURES TO EXPAND SERVICES FOR FOSTER YOUTH, TO
PROTECT FARMWORKERS, TO FUND SPECIAL EDUCATION, TO PRESERVE
OLD GROWTH REDWOODS, TO RESTRICT GUNS AND TO EXTEND
BENEFITS FOR THE POOR. >> HIS LEGACY INCLUDES HAVING
SHAPED WELFARE REFORM, STRENGTHENED LABOR RIGHTS,
CHAMPIONED THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT AND RAISING
THE FEDERAL MINIMUM WAGE IN SHORT ADVANCING THE MYRIAD
PRIORITIES THAT REPRESENT THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY AT ITS VERY
BEST. IT IS PERHAPS NO ACCIDENT THEN
THAT HE WOULD ALSO GO ON TO SERVE AS ONE OF THE STATE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY'S MOST ACCOMPLISHED CHAIRS IN THAT
ROLE. IN FACT, HE WAS CREDITED BY
FORMER GOVERNOR JERRY BROWN AS SOMEONE WHO WILL GO DOWN AS THE
GUY WHO GAVE LIFE AND STRUCTURE AND SUCCESS TO THE CALIFORNIA
DEMOCRATIC PARTY. WHATEVER ELSE HE WAS HOWEVER,
JOHN BURTON WAS NEVER SHY ABOUT BEING HIMSELF.
FIRST AND FOREMOST HE WAS RUMPLED, DIRECT AND FAMOUSLY
PROFANE. BUT HIS BLUSTER ALWAYS CAME
FROM A PLACE OF LOVE. HE HAD A KNACK FOR CUTTING
THROUGH POLITICS AS USUAL WITH BLUNT HONESTY, SHARP HUMOR
AND DEEP HUMANITY. HE COULD NEGOTIATE WITH
GOVERNORS AND PRESIDENTS, SING SONGS ON THE SENATE FLOOR WITH
REPUBLICAN COLLEAGUES AND STILL FIND TIME TO DELIVER BLANKETS
TO THOSE SLEEPING ON THE STREETS.
HIS LEADERSHIP EXTENDED BEYOND THE CAPITALS IN WASHINGTON
AND SACRAMENTO. HOWEVER, THROUGH HIS NONPROFIT
JOHN BURTON ADVOCATES FOR YOUTH HE CHAMPIONED FOSTER KIDS
AND HOMELESS YOUTH. HE WORKED TO HELP THOUSANDS OF
YOUNG PEOPLE BUILD BRIGHTER FUTURES.
AMONG THE MULTITUDE OF ADMIRABLE QUALITIES FOR WHICH
HE HAS BEEN REMEMBERED AND PRAISED IN RECENT DAYS,
JOHN BURTON'S VULNERABILITY AND COURAGE BACK IN THE 1980S.
IN ACKNOWLEDGING HIS STRUGGLE WITH DRUG ADDICTION IS WHAT
MOST INSPIRED ME. HE SPOKE OPENLY ABOUT IT AND IN
SO DOING GAVE HOPE TO COUNTLESS OTHERS WHO'VE STRUGGLED WITH
ADDICTION SIMILARLY AND WHO MAY HAVE DOUBTED THEIR OWN
PROSPECTS TO GET ANOTHER CHANCE IN ITS AFTERMATH.
HIS RECOVERY WAS NOT JUST A PERSONAL TRIUMPH.
IT WAS A POWERFUL REMINDER OF REDEMPTION POSSIBILITY.
AND HE USED HIS SECOND ACT IN POLITICS TO FIGHT HARDER
THAN EVER BEFORE FOR THE UNDERDOG.
JOHN BURTON EMBODIED PASSION, CONVICTION AND RESILIENCE.
HE HELD BECAUSE HE CARED. CALIFORNIA IS BETTER, FAIRER
AND MORE COMPASSIONATE BECAUSE OF IT.
IN ADDITION TO HIS DAUGHTER KUMIKO AND HER CHILDREN, ONE
AND MIKALA, JOHN BURTON IS SURVIVED BY MICHELLE BURTON,
HIS FIRST WIFE AND MOTHER OF KIMIKO AND GRANDMOTHER OF JUAN
AND MIKALA. OUR CONDOLENCES AND OUR HEARTS
GO OUT TO ALL OF THEM AS WELL AS TO HIS FRIENDS, LOVED ONES
AND ADMIRERS. REST IN POWER, SENATOR, AND MAY
YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING. >> AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR
CHAN THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENDOZA AND I DEFINITELY WANT
TO JOIN THIS JUST REMEMBERING JON BURTON.
BUT I FIRST WANT TO SAY YOU KNOW I DO NOT HAVE A DEEP.
I DID NOT HAVE A DEEP RELATIONSHIP WITH HIM AND AS
MANY HAD. BUT TODAY I THINK PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN AND I ARE BOTH WEARING THE BOBBY PAN THAT
ACTUALLY WAS GIVEN BY FRANCIS SHEA ON OUR TEAM AND IS IT'S
LIKE PART OF HER FAMILY TREASURE.
AND I THINK THAT'S HOW JOHN BURTON IMPACT EVERYONE SOME
MAYBE VERY DEEPLY AND PERSONALLY AND SOME LIKE ME
AND FRANCIS SHEA AND AND PRESIDENT RANDOM AND I WILL SAY
I, I GOT TO KNOW HIM ACTUALLY WHEN I WAS RUNNING MY FIRST
TERM AND AS A CANDIDATE I REMEMBER AND I THINK THAT THAT
SO MUCH ABOUT HIM HE DID NOT HAVE CURSE WORDS WHEN I CALL
HIM AND WHEN HE PICKED UP THE PHONE BUT HE WAS VERY
STRAIGHTFORWARD AND SIMPLE. I AS A CANDIDATE OF COURSE
ALWAYS IT'S LIKE WOW, WHAT AN HONOR THAT YOU PICK UP THE
PHONE. SENATOR BURTON AND WOULD LOVE
TO HAVE COFFEE WITH YOU AND HOPE THAT YOU KNOW, YOU GET
TO I GET TO KNOW YOU AND YOU GET TO KNOW ME.
BUT HE WAS VERY STRAIGHTFORWARD.
HE SAID NOPE, WE DON'T NEED COFFEE.
I SAID, OH NOW THIS MUST BE A REJECTION THAT'S COMING.
>> AND THEN HE SAID THERE'S MIKE CASEY AND ANYBODY WHO
KNOWS MY CASEY LOGO TOO. DOES MIKE CASEY DO MY CASEY
ENDORSE YOU? I SAID YES INDEED HE DID
AND LOCAL TWO DID AND HE SAID THAT'S GOOD ENOUGH FOR ME.
>> YOU HAVE MY ENDORSEMENT. GOODBYE.
AND MANY OF THERE WAS NO MORE WORDS TO BE SAID.
>> BUT I THINK THAT WHILE THAT WAS SHORT AND BRIEF, I THINK
THAT I LEARNED SO MUCH IN THAT BRIEF MINUTE.
>> ONE HE KNEW WHO HE WAS. HE KNEW HIS VALUES.
HE KNEW HIS ALLY MIKE CASEY. HE TRUSTED HIM AND HE KNEW WHAT
IT WAS ABOUT THE LABOR MOVEMENT AND WE HAVE LABOR AND BEING
PART OF THE MOVEMENT THEN HE'S PART OF IT TOO.
SO I THINK THAT EVEN THOUGH A SHORT BRIEF CONVERSATION I TOOK
THAT WITH ME AND CARRIED WITH ME I THINK FOR MY FOR FOR THOSE
YEARS I DID IT SINCE I TOOK OFFICE BUT I THINK ALSO FOR MY
REMAINING TIME HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND AS A MEMBER OF
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND I'M SURE THAT THIS IS JUST
ONE OF THE MANY, MANY STORIES THAT ALL SAN FRANCISCANS
EXPERIENCE DURING THEIR TIME AND INTERACT AND BE AGAIN, YOU
KNOW, VERY BRIEF LIKE I DID OR SOMEONE THAT I HAVE A VERY LONG
RELATIONSHIP LIKE MAYBE OUR SPEAKER EMERITA PELOSI AND MANY
OTHER POLITICIANS AND YOU LIKED IT AND COMMUNITY LEADERS LIKE
MIKE CASEY IN THIS TOWN FOR THAT I AM JUST TRULY GRATEFUL
TO EVEN HAVE THAT BRIEF CONVERSATION AND THAT NOT ONLY
THAT HE WILL BE GREATLY MISS I THINK THAT HE SHOULD ARE TO BE
A SHINING LEGENDARY EXAMPLE OF WHAT ANY ELECTED ANY SAN
FRANCISCANS SHOULD BE FIGHTING FOR.
SAN FRANCISCO YOU CAN CURSE YOU DON'T HAVE TO CURSE BUT I THINK
WITH THE SAME PASSIONATE SPIRIT AND FIGHTING SPIRIT AND MOST
IMPORTANT SAN FRANCISCO VALUE. >> SO THANK YOU THANK THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR JAN THANK YOU AGAIN SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR DOING
THIS I FEEL I SENT A LITTLE MESSAGE TO SENATOR BURTON'S
DAUGHTER SAYING THAT I JUST FEEL I FEEL SO LUCKY TO HAVE
KNOWN HIM A LITTLE BIT NOT MAYBE AS MUCH AS SUPERVISOR
DORSEY BUT TO HAVE HAD A LITTLE BIT A FEW OPPORTUNITIES TO GET
TO KNOW HIM A LITTLE AND MORE. SO I FEEL FORTUNATE TO HAVE TO
HAVE BEEN IT TO HAVE LIVED THE ENTIRETY OF MY LIFE IN A
CALIFORNIA AND A SAN FRANCISCO THAT WAS IN MANY WAYS DEFINED
BY THE BURDENS. I THINK YOU HAVE TO GO BACK TO
LIKE THE 1950S TO SEE THE BEGINNING OF THEIR INFLUENCE
AND HIS DEATH, YOU KNOW, SORT OF PUTS A BOOKEND.
BUT IF YOU THINK ABOUT WHAT A SAN FOR WHAT IT MEANT TO BE A
SAN FRANCISCO DEMOCRAT FOR YOU KNOW HALF A CENTURY REALLY IT
WAS A LOT ABOUT WHAT THE BURTONS UNDERSTOOD ABOUT WHAT
IT WAS TO BE A DEMOCRAT AND I THINK SUPERVISOR CHAN SPOKE
ABOUT THAT BUT FIGHTING FOR WORKING PEOPLE KNOWING THAT
YOU'RE ON THE SIDE OF THE UNDERDOG I THINK I'VE SPOKEN
HERE ABOUT THAT STATUE ON THE MARINA OR AT FORT MASON THAT I
THINK IS SO GREAT. BUT IT'S JOHN BURTON'S BROTHER
PHILIP BURTON WHICH HAS THAT LITTLE SPEECH SORT OF POKING
OUT OF HIS HIS POCKET WHICH YOU KNOW, IS A LITTLE TOO SECTION
OF THE QUOTE. I MEAN THE FULL QUOTE IS THE
ONLY WAY TO DEAL WITH EXPLOITERS IS TO TERRORIZE THE
. AND I THINK THAT THAT IDEA WAS
SO CORE AND BASIC TO SO MANY OF THE PEOPLE WHO WERE CREATING
YOU KNOW, SO MUCH OF WHAT GOOD THINGS HAVE HAPPENED IN THE
UNITED STATES FOR FOR LIKE A HALF A CENTURY.
SO IT'S IT'S PRETTY EXTRAORDINARY.
THE OTHER THING I THINK IS WORTH NOTING ABOUT JOHN BURTON
I MEAN HE WAS NOT YOU KNOW, PROBABLY A I MEAN HE WASN'T
THAT YOU WOULDN'T THINK OF HIM AS A SENSITIVE MAN BUT BUT HE
DID OPEN THE DOOR FOR AN EXTRA ORDINARY NUMBER OF VERY
POWERFUL AND EFFECTIVE WOMEN OR HE HELPED A LOT OF VERY
POWERFUL AND EFFECTIVE WOMEN. THERE WAS A PERIOD WHERE THE
ENTIRE NORTHERN CALIFORNIA CONGRESSIONAL DELEGATION I
THINK WAS MADE UP OF WOMEN AND THAT WAS A LOT A LOT OF
THOSE WERE WOMEN WHO HAD BEEN PROTEGES OF OF JOHN BURTON'S
AND I THINK YOU KNOW FROM DIANNE FEINSTEIN TO BARBARA
BOXER TO NANCY PELOSI TO JACKIE SPEIER TO ANNA ESHOO AND AND
FIONA MARR. SO MANY PEOPLE WHO BENEFITED
FROM THAT AND OF COURSE THE BURTONS DID A TON FOR THE
COMMUNITY AS WELL AND SO FOR LOTS OF COMMUNITIES I THINK
THEY WERE REALLY PART OF THAT TRANSFER TRANSFORMATION THAT
HAPPENED IN NORTHERN CALIFORNIA THAT WE'RE YOU KNOW AS WE FACE
CONFLICT ABOUT WHAT IT MEANS TO BE AN AMERICAN AND WHAT AMERICA
IS ABOUT, I THINK CALIFORNIA KIND OF KNOWS WHAT IT'S ABOUT
IN LARGE PART BECAUSE OF THE BURTONS SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
DORSEY MADAM CLERK WE CAN GO BACK TO ROLL CALL.
>> NEXT UP IS SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO.
>> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. TODAY I'M INTRODUCING AN
ORDINANCE TO EXPAND THE CITY'S COMMUNITY POLICING POLICY.
THE COMMUNITY POLICING POLICY WAS ADOPTED NEARLY 15 YEARS AGO
TO PROVIDE GUIDANCE TO THE POLICE DEPARTMENT ON BUILDING
RELATIONSHIPS AND MAINTAINING TRUST WITH THE COMMUNITIES THEY
SERVE AS THE NEEDS OF OUR COMMUNITIES EVOLVE OVER TIME WE
MUST ALSO PERIODICALLY REVIEW AND UPDATE OUR PUBLIC SAFETY
POLICIES TO ENSURE OUR RESIDENTS, WORKERS
AND BUSINESSES CONTINUE TO FEEL SAFE.
THE SUNSET DISTRICT IS SERVED BY TERRYVILLE STATION WHICH IS
ONE OF THE LARGEST GEOGRAPHIC POLICE DISTRICTS IN THE CITY
FROM OCEAN BEACH TO TWIN PEAKS, GOLDEN GATE PARK TO I 280
AND THE DALY CITY BORDER TERRYVILLE STATION IS HOME TO
CULTURALLY DIVERSE NEIGHBORHOODS AND A WIDE RANGE
OF ECONOMIC BACKGROUNDS THROUGH COMMUNITY POLICING WORK OUT OF
TERRIBLE STATION IDENTIFIED TWO KEY COMPONENTS MISSING FROM THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT'S CURRENT POLICY THAT THIS ORDINANCE
SEEKS TO ADDRESS. >> FIRST, WHILE TODAY'S
COMMUNITY POLICING POLICY EMPHASIZES THE IMPORTANCE OF
INCLUSIVE PROGRAMING AND COMMUNITY RELATIONS FOR THE
VULNERABLE STAKEHOLDER GROUPS PARTICULARLY YOUTH, LGBTQ
INDIVIDUALS, COMMUNITIES OF COLOR AND UNHOUSED RESIDENTS
THE INTENT OF THIS ORDINANCE HELPS MAKE CERTAIN OTHER
VULNERABLE POPULATIONS ARE INCLUDED IN THE DEPARTMENT'S
EFFORTS. SPECIFICALLY IT ADDS SENIORS
AND INDIVIDUALS WITH LIMITED ENGLISH PROFICIENCY TO GROUPS
WHO OFTEN FACE BARRIERS TO ACCESSING AND ENGAGING PUBLIC
SAFETY PERSONNEL AND RESOURCES IN THE SUNSET DISTRICT FOR
COMMUNITY SAFETY LIAISON HAS BEEN RECOGNIZED AS A BRIDGE TO
THESE TWO COMMUNITIES LAUNCHING TARGETED ENGAGEMENT PROGRAMS
THAT HAVE EXPANDED AND DEEPENED OUR POLICE DEPARTMENT'S
RELATIONSHIPS WITH RESIDENTS, WORKERS AND BUSINESS OWNERS.
I'M INCREDIBLY, INCREDIBLY PROUD OF OUR LIAISONS WORK
LEADING WIDELY ACCESSIBLE MULTI-LANE ROAD CRIME
PREVENTION PROGRAMS TO BUILD THAT TRUST AND CONNECT THE
SUNSET DISTRICT TO TERRIBLE STATION IN NEW WAYS.
SECOND, THE CURRENT POLICY DOES NOT ACKNOWLEDGE THE IMPORTANT
ROLE THAT CIVILIAN STAFF PLAY IN COMMUNITY POLICING.
CIVILIAN STAFF ARE OFTEN THE CONSISTENT PRESENCE AT
NEIGHBORHOOD STATIONS REMAINING IN THEIR ROLES FAR LONGER THAN
MANY OFFICERS SERGEANTS, LIEUTENANTS OR CAPTAINS.
BECAUSE OF THIS CONTINUITY THEY ARE UNIQUELY POSITIONED TO
BUILD LASTING RELATIONSHIPS WITH RESIDENTS AND COMMUNITY
ORGANIZATIONS. RECOGNIZING THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS
IS ESSENTIAL TO STRENGTHENING THE TRUST AND CONTINUITY THAT
COMMUNITY POLICING DEPENDS ON. LASTLY, I ACKNOWLEDGE THAT SOME
COMMUNITIES ARE NOT COMFORTABLE APPROACHING A UNIFORMED ARMED
OFFICER A REGULARLY DRESSED CIVILIAN CAN IMMEDIATELY
DISSOLVE ANY WARINESS OR HESITATION WHEN ASKING FOR
ASSISTANCE FROM PUBLIC SAFETY PERSONNEL.
A CIVILIAN STAFFER CAN ALSO PRIORITIZE THEIR TIME WORKING
ONE ON ONE WITH MEMBERS IN THE COMMUNITY ON ADMINISTRATIVE
MATTERS WHICH MAY NOT BE POSSIBLE FOR UNIFORMED OFFICERS
WHO NEED TO PIVOT AND RESPOND TO AN URGENT CRISIS OR
EMERGENCY. >> I GREATLY APPRECIATE
SUPERVISOR SHANNON CHEN'S EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP OF THIS
ORDINANCE AND THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR CONSIDERING THIS
UPDATE TO OUR COMMUNITY POLICING POLICY AND THE REST I
SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
AND ENGARDIO AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION THAT
CALLS ON GOVERNOR NEWSOM TO COMMUTE EVERY DEATH SENTENCE
IN CALIFORNIA AND REDIRECT THOSE RESOURCES TO THE
SURVIVORS OF VIOLENT CRIME WHO NEED THEM MOST.
>> WE AS CALIFORNIANS PRIDE OURSELVES ON PROGRESS.
WE BAN THE USE OF GAS CHAMBERS. WE LED THE NATION
IN MORATORIUMS. BUT WHILE EXECUTIONS ARE
PAUSED, DEATH SENTENCES REMAIN IN PLACE AND OUR DEATH ROW
PERSISTS AS A RELIC OF CRUELTY .
SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG STOOD AGAINST THE DEATH PENALTY
BECAUSE IT IS UNJUST, RACIALLY BIASED AND DEEPLY FLAWED.
>> TWO OUT OF EVERY THREE PEOPLE SENTENCED TO DEATH
IN CALIFORNIA ARE PEOPLE OF COLOR.
>> WE KNOW THAT DEATH SENTENCES ARE MORE LIKELY WHEN VICTIMS
ARE WHITE AND THAT THE MAJORITY OF HOMICIDES WITH BLACK OR
LATINO VICTIMS GO UNSOLVED. SINCE 1981, EIGHT CALIFORNIA
GUNS ALL MEN OF COLOR HAVE BEEN EXONERATED AND RELEASED FROM
DEATH ROW. >> MEANWHILE, CALIFORNIA HAS
SPENT $5 BILLION SINCE 1977 ON A DEATH PENALTY SYSTEM THAT HAS
RESULTED IN JUST 13 EXECUTIONS. >> CONTINUING THIS BROKEN
SYSTEM WOULD COST US ANOTHER $600 MILLION.
>> THOSE ARE RESOURCES THAT COULD AND SHOULD BE INVESTED
IN VIOLENCE PREVENTION, TREATMENT AND SERVICES FOR
SURVIVORS OF CRIME. >> ESPECIALLY AT A TIME WHEN
FEDERAL CUTS HAVE ALREADY DEVASTATED PROGRAMS ACROSS OUR
STATE. >> GOVERNOR NEWSOM HAS ALREADY
TAKEN HISTORIC ACTION BY HALTING EXECUTIONS
AND DISMANTLING THE DEATH CHAMBER.
THIS RESOLUTION ASKS HIM TO TAKE THE NEXT STEP TO COMMUTE
ALL DEATH SENTENCES AND MOVE CALIFORNIA TOWARD A FUTURE
ROOTED IN JUSTICE, HEALING AND PUBLIC SAFETY.
>> IT'S TIME FOR CALIFORNIA TO CLOSE DEATH ROW ONCE AND FOR
ALL. IT'S TIME TO END A SYSTEM THAT
IS RACIST, COSTLY AND INHUMANE AND TO BUILD ONE THAT TRULY
DELIVERS SAFETY, DIGNITY AND JUSTICE FOR EVERY
COMMUNITY. THANK YOU.
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
AND FOR HOUSEKEEPING PURPOSES YOU NEED ON THE IN MEMORIAM FOR
FOUR FORMER SENATOR BURTON FOR THAT TO COME FROM THE FULL
BOARD. YOU WANT ME TO GAVEL DOWN ON
THAT? >> YES, PLEASE, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT. >> RIGHT AT THIS TIME THE BOARD
WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT. PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER. YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MAYORAL
APPEARANCE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED ITEMS 25 THROUGH 30
TWO THOSE ARE FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE
AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA BUT MUST BE
WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
ALL OTHER CONTENT HAS BEEN REPORTED OUT TO THE BOARD BY AN
APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE WHERE THE PUBLIC COMMENT REQUIREMENT
OCCURRED. WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO
MINUTES. >> WELCOME.
WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER. >> JUST QUICKLY LET ME REPEAT
WHAT I SAID BEFORE THE SHOW STARTED HERE AGAIN WHEN THE
MAYOR WAS HERE SO YOU CAN'T FAKE BEAUTY I REPEAT AND YOU
ARE DONE AS PEDOPHILES OR IF YOU DO YOU SEE THAT'S THE WAY
IT IS. THE FUTURE IS SELF-CONTROL BY
THE WAY. DEATH PENALTY IT'S INTERESTING
BECAUSE IN FRANCE THERE WAS A PRESIDENT CALLED MITTERRAND.
FIRST THING HE DID IS ABOLISH THE DEATH PENALTY.
I THINK IT WAS TO COVER THE PEDOPHILES BECAUSE HE KNEW THAT
NO MATTER WHAT IF YOU ARE PEDOPHILES YOU ARE IN BIG
TROUBLE. IS HE THE ONLY OTHER OPTION IS
ABORTION? >> BUT THEN YEAH, LOOK, NO
SAFETY WE PEDOPHILES IN SOCIETIES IN GENERAL AND LET
ALONE IN ANY FORM OF GOVERNMENTS OUT WE DON'T WANT
THEM IF YOU DISAGREE YOU ARE IN BIG TROUBLE.
>> YOU ARE PEDOPHILES THEN THAT'S IT.
>> OKAY. THE FISHERY SELF-CONTROL.
WELL, IT'S BECAUSE SELF-CONTROL IS WHAT REGULATES YOU SEE
EXISTENCE. THAT'S WHY THERE IS ETERNITY
BECAUSE OF SELF-CONTROL. SO YOU CONTROL YOUR EMOTIONS.
>> YOU FOCUS THE WORLD'S BEAUTY .
>> YOU SEE YOURSELF SELF-CONTROL.
SO GLOBALIZATION CAN ONLY WORK IF YOU PROMOTE INDIVIDUALISM
TOWARDS SELF-CONTROL LEARNING THEN YOU SHARE YOU CAN HAVE A
SORT OF GLOBALIZATION OF INDIVIDUAL INDIVIDUALISM WHICH
MEANS NO GOVERNMENT OBVIOUSLY ONLY SUPERVISORS.
YOU HAVE SUPERVISORS NOT ELECTED BUT SELECTED BY DRAWING
FOR ONE YEAR ONLY. THAT'S THE FUTURE.
OTHERWISE YES, WE'RE GOING TO CREATE OUR OWN CURRENCY.
>> WE DON'T NEED ANY GOVERNMENT.
ARE YOU JOKING? OKAY, STEP BY STEP STOP WORKING
FOR THE BITTER FIGHTS THAT YOU FOCUS ON BEAUTY.
IT'S THE ONLY FUTURE. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER, MR. WASHINGTON THANK YOU.
TODAY I'M HERE TO DO A PRESENTATION TO THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. >> I HAVE HERE I LIKE TO PASS
OUT TO EACH SUPERVISOR A DOCUMENT OF OUR LAST WEEK'S
FILLMORE CORRIDOR. AMBASSADOR FILLMORE TOUR IS
VERY SUCCESSFUL. >> IT'S ONE OF THREE THAT WE
PLANNING ON DOING THIS YEAR. >> SO ANYWAY I'M ALSO HERE TO
TO PUT OUR SUPERVISOR DISTRICT FIVE AND THE MAYOR ON NOTICE
AND SUPPOSEDLY SUPPOSED TO BE NEGOTIATING TO TRY TO DO A
COMMUNITY MEETING IN THE WEST IN ADDITION I GUESS THEY'RE
TRYING TO FIND THE LOCATION, THE TIME AND PLACE BUT I'M HERE
TO HELP OUT WHAT I CAN. >> I AM ALSO COMING TO THIS
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO ME TO TALK ABOUT MY LEGACY AND I
HEARD JOHN TALK ABOUT BURDENS AND THE REST OF THEM BUT I
DON'T KNOW IF YOU ALL KNOW I WAS THROUGH EIGHT
ADMINISTRATIONS CEREMONIES, EIGHT MAYORS I BRING THROUGH
ALL THE WAY UP TO THIS WHEN I'M TRYING TO FIND A RELATIONSHIP I
WANT THEM TO HAVE WITH THIS MAYOR AND SUPERVISORS.
I WAS AROUND WHEN THE SUPERVISORS WAS JUST GENERALLY
ELECTED NOT DISTRICTS. SO YOU COULD IMAGINE YOU KNOW,
MY LIFE SPAN HERE AT CITY HALL WHICH I CALL SILLY HALL HAS
PERCEIVED MOST OF EVERYBODY IN HERE EXCEPT FOR A FEW.
SO BUT I'M HERE SPECIFICALLY TO PIT THE SUPERVISOR DISTRICT
FIVE AND THE MAYOR ON NOTICE THAT THE FILLMORE CORRIDOR
AMBASSADOR IS HERE TO DO A PARTNERSHIP COMMUNITY MEETING
IN THE WEST IN ADDITION WHERE IT'S NEEDED.
I'M NOT GOING TO GO OVER THE PROBLEMS BECAUSE I DON'T HAVE
ENOUGH TIME BUT THEY KNOW THE PROBLEMS THAT WE HAVE BUT I
BASICALLY WANTED TO GIVE A BROCHURE OF OUR TOUR AND INVITE
JOAN ALLEN TO KNOW OUR NEXT ONE BUT THE NEXT COMMUNITY MEETING
I WOULD LIKE TO HAVE WITH THE SUPERVISOR AND THE
MAYOR COLLABORATING WITH THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU MR. WASHINGTON.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. THANK YOU VERY MUCH TO THE
CHAIR AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS JIM BURTON
WORKED WITH FIRST CLASS, SECOND CLASS AND NO CLASS.
IT DIDN'T MATTER TO HIM WHO YOU WERE.
YOU WERE PART OF THE FAMILY THAT WAS A BURDENED FAMILY.
>> BUT THE ISSUES THAT WERE BROUGHT UP, THE IMPORTANCE OF
SUSTAINABILITY WHICH IS A BASE TO LIVE IN IS SOMETHING I'M AN
EXPERT IN. YOU CAN CHECK THE RECORD AT
NORTH BEACH PLACE NORTH BEACH PUBLIC HOUSING I WAS THE
PRESIDENT OF THE ASSOCIATION AT THAT TIME TO WALK INTO FOR A
HEAVENLY CAUSE. >> I HAVE THE EXPERIENCE.
I HAVE THE KNOW HOW HOW TO DEAL WITH FEDERAL LAW WHEN IT COMES
TO PUBLIC HOUSING SO THEREFORE I CAN BE CALLED ON BY ANYONE
THAT WANTS TO FINISH THE JOB. 128 UNITS I MEAN 228 UNITS ONE
FOR ONE REPLACEMENT ARE SITTING RIGHT THERE.
IT'S PROOF WITH BUSINESSES UNDERNEATH IT ALONG WITH THE
CITY GOVERNMENT. WE MADE THAT HAPPEN BUT ALL
DOWNTOWN MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION ALWAYS IT BEEN THIS IS
FISHERMAN'S WHARF ASSOCIATE ATION DOWNTOWN ASSOCIATION ALSO
WITH TAX CREDITS GOVERNOR SO WE ALSO WORK WITH REPUBLICANS DAN
YOU DO HAVE A REPUBLICAN COMMITTEE HERE YOU NEED TO TALK
TO YOU NEED VOTES FROM BOTH SIDES.
JUST A REMINDER THAT'S WHAT WE WORKED WITH SAN FRANCISCO
SPECIAL IT WORKS AT EVERY PARTY THERE IS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME. NEXT SPEAKER GOOD AFTERNOON
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> FOR THE RECORD MY NAME IS
CHRIS WARD KLEIN AND ALSO SERGEANT KLEIN OF THE UNITED
STATES MARINE CORPS. LAST WEEK I GAVE A REPORT TO
THE BOARD IN THE POLICE COMMISSION.
SO AT THIS POINT LET THE SHERIFF THE POLICE CHIEF, THE
FBI AND THE DOD MOVE FORWARD ON ACTION ITEMS ACROSS THE STREET
AT THE WAR MEMORIAL BUILDING THERE ARE BANNERS THAT TELL THE
STORY BEFORE, DURING AND AFTER WAR AND WHAT IT LOOKS LIKE THAT
LOOKS LIKE SERIOUS NATIONAL INCIDENTS WAR, IMMIGRATION,
COMMERCE, TARIFFS AND CONGRESSIONAL LINES ARE
BEING REDRAWN. WE ARE JUST A FEW YEARS REMOVED
FROM IRAQ AND AFGHANISTAN. EVERY DAY I WALK AROUND GAUGING
THE TEMPERATURE OF OUR COMMUNITY AND PEOPLE ARE UPSET,
EXTREMELY UPSET. I KNOW YOU'RE READY TO FIGHT
ABOUT THIS TECHNOLOGY WAR, IMMIGRATION, THE COMMERCE, THE
TARIFFS AND THE WAR THAT WE ARE CURRENTLY IN.
WE NEED LEADERS SUCH AS THE ONES IN THIS ROOM TO PROMOTE
PEACE AND BE WILLING TO WORK ACROSS THE LINES AND WITH
OTHERS YOU HAVE NOT IN THE PAST THERE WILL BE SERIOUS QUESTIONS
AND CONVERSATIONS SUCH AS IN 1979 WHEN MY FATHER DIED
AND I WAS EXTREMELY UPSET BECAUSE I DIDN'T UNDERSTAND
ABOUT WAR MY LITTLE LEAGUE COACH CAME OVER AND TALKED TO
ME TO NEVER GIVE UP AND GO BACK AND PLAY BASEBALL.
>> YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE THOSE CONVERSATIONS GOING FORWARD
IN 1979 JIMMY CARTER ASKED FIVE OF HIS CABINET MEMBERS TO
RESIGN KNOWING THAT HE WOULD LOSE THE ELECTION TO BRING
PEACE AND COMMUNITY TO THE UNITED STATES AND 1979 IN THE
EARLY 80S, SENATOR JOHN BURTON WAS ALSO VERY INSTRUMENTAL
IN THE TRANSITION FROM WAR TO PEACE IN THE 70S.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> THANK YOU.
HELLO MY NAME IS LIAM MACGYVER. GLAD YOU ALL HAD A GREAT
VACATION. LET ME SHARE MINE.
>> ON AUGUST 8TH I WITNESSED A FRIEND GET VIOLENTLY ATTACKED
OLD AND ARRESTED BY ICE. I WITNESSED THIS HAPPEN TO
ANOTHER COMRADE AT 630 SANSOM. IT WAS TERRIFYING.
I WAS SCREAMING NOT OUT OF FURIOUS INDIGNATION BUT OUT OF
TERROR. I YELLED AT THE ICE AGENT BODY
CRUSHING ONE COMRADE CAN THEY BREATHE?
AS I WATCHED MY COMRADES EYES BULGE OUT TO THEIR FACE SEEMING
TO SHAKE KNOW THEY COULD NOT BREATHE.
THE AGENT SAID OF COURSE THEY CAN.
I DON'T KNOW HOW HE KNOW THAT. THIS FELT DIFFERENT THAN
WITNESSING ICE INDISCRIMINATELY RAMMING THEIR VANS INTO
PROTESTERS ARE POINTING THEIR WEAPONS AT US.
ONE MASKED MAN POINTED HIS TASER AT ME AS I FOLLOWED THEM,
TAKING MY FRIEND AWAY. I COULDN'T STOP FOLLOWING
DESPITE THE THREATS LITERALLY POINTED AT MY FACE, MY EYES
BARELY REGISTERING THE BEAMING WHITE LIGHT AT THE TASER AT THE
TASER GUNS TIP. I WAS WITNESSING I SAID DUCKED
TWO OF US NOT KNOWING IF I'D EVER SEE THEM AGAIN WOULD THEY
BE TRANSFERRED OUT OF STATES? WOULD THEY BE SENT TO A
CONCENTRATION CAMP? WHO THE KNOWS?
>> WE CERTAINLY DIDN'T AT THE TIME AS ICE MARCHED TO
ABOLITION LISTS THOSE FIGHTING FOR THE FREEDOM OF OTHERS PAST
THEIR BLACK BAR FENCE AND INTO THE BRUTALIST ARCHITECTURE
BUILDING. I SCREAMED MY FRIEND'S NAME AS
I WATCHED THEM DISAPPEAR BEHIND CLOSED DOORS.
I LATER CRIED IN A COMRADE'S EMBRACE AFTER ANOTHER COMRADE
WATCHED MY EYES AT THE BURNING CHEMICAL AGENT ICE DEPLOYED
AGAINST US. >> I FELT LIKE VOMITING, LIKE
SCREAMING. I FELT I NEEDED TO EXPEL FROM
MY BODY WHAT I HAD JUST ENDURED AND WITNESS.
>> THEN THE MEDIA CHILL ROLLED IN LIKE A HEAVY FOG ONLY
MISSION LOCAL REPORTED ON THIS HAPPENING.
I SPOKE TO OTHER NEWS OUTLETS BUT THEY DIDN'T RUN THE STORY.
TWO U.S. CITIZENS WERE ILLEGALLY ATTACKED AND ARRESTED
BY ICE AND SILENCE. THE FASCISM WAS GETTING WORSE
AND I WAS AMONG A POOL OF PROTESTERS THAT FASCISM BEGAN
PLUCKING AWAY ONE BY ONE. I FELT EVEN MORE SCARED FOR MY
COMRADES AND MYSELF. ON AUGUST 20TH THIRD, U.S.
CITIZEN AND JELLICOE LATINA WAS ATTACKED.
>> IT DISAPPEARED FOR 24 HOURS AND IS CURRENTLY BEING TRIED BY
THE FEDS. >> I FORGET THEIR SUPERVISORS
OR MAYORS HERE THAT CARE ABOUT THIS KIND OF STUFF.
>> I REALLY FORGET. REMIND ME PLEASE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS APPLE KRONK. I'M A DISTRICT SEVEN RESIDENT
AND A COMMUNITY ADVOCATE. I'M HERE TO SAY THANK YOU
SUPERVISORS FOR PUTTING INTO ACTION THE SETTLEMENT BETWEEN
THE COALITION ON HOMELESSNESS AND THE CITY.
>> I'M GOING TO PAUSE YOUR TIME, MA'AM.
THAT ITEM IS NOT ELIGIBLE FOR YOUR COMMENT.
>> NO, MA'AM. I'M SORRY I'M NOT GOOD AT THIS
BUT. ALL RIGHT.
>> THANK YOU FOR COMING DOWN THIS AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON .
I'M HERE TO I'M A MUNI BOOSTER, BY THE WAY.
I DON'T DRIVE. I TAKE COMMUNITY TRANSPORTATION
AND WHEN ALL OF A SUDDEN I SEE THAT MAYOR LURIE HAS PROPOSED
THAT THE SOLUTION TO MUNI IS TO GET A PARCEL TAX PASSED.
WELL THE PARCEL TAX IS A VERY REGRESSIVE TAX THAT PEOPLE ON
THE WEST SIDE AND THAT'S DISTRICT FOUR AND DISTRICT ONE
ARE THE ONES THAT ARE GOING TO BE SUPPORTING THE DOWNTOWN
ENTRANCE. WELL WHY DO THEY WANT TO DO A
PARCEL TAX? THAT'S BECAUSE A GENERAL
PROPERTY TAX IS NOT GOING TO PASS BECAUSE YOU DO A PROPERTY
TAX. EVERYBODY IS ALERTED.
THE WHOLE CITY IS ALERTED. YOU DO A PARCEL TASK, YOU GO
AROUND THE CITY AND ASK ANYBODY IF THEY ANY RESIDENT IF THEY
KNOW WHAT A PARCEL TAX IS 90% 95% OF THE RESIDENTS SIMPLY DO
NOT KNOW AND WHO DID THEY AFFECT MOST?
THE PEOPLE WHO ARE THEIR HOMEOWNERS AND THE HOMEOWNERS
WERE NOT INVITED TO MAYOR LURIE'S SPECIAL COMMITTEE
ALL ON THAT COMMITTEE WERE BOOSTERS OF OF THE MUNI MUNI
RIDERS BUT MUNI UP AND ANYWAY THEY WERE BASICALLY BASICALLY
BOOSTERS PARCEL TAXES, PARCEL TAXES, PARCEL TAX THIS IS GOING
TO BE A BIG FIGHT AND DON'T USE A TERM OR DON'T USE A TAX THAT
NOBODY REALLY UNDERSTANDS. I UNDERSTAND WHAT A PARCEL
TAXES ARE GOING TO HAVE TO PARCELS.
I'LL BE PAYING MORE THAN THE MILLENNIAL TOWER DOWN THERE
THAT'S ONLY ON ONE PARCEL. SO WHEN YOU GET DOWN TO UP
DOING YOUR TAX CALCULATIONS REALIZE THAT NO BODY REALLY
KNOWS WHAT A PARCEL TAX IS. ONE PARCEL ONE TAX.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER BOOK UP THE THING HERE AS I'VE
GOT TV PLEASE THIS IS A GREAT BOOK.
REMEMBER I WAS GOING TO TALK ABOUT RFK BOOK THE REAL ANTHONY
FAUCI AND THEN THE PERSON GUY THAT SAT IN YOUR SEAT STARTED
TALKING ABOUT THE NEW YEAR AND SO HE SWAYED ME OFF ON
TALKING ABOUT THE SABATHIA. >> BUT IT'S A POWERFUL BOOK THE
REAL ANTHONY FAUCI HE'S GOT LIKE 2000 FOOTNOTES
AND EVERYBODY SHOULD READ IT AND I THANK GOD FOR KENNEDY.
HE'S DOING A GREAT JOB IN EXPOSING THE LIES OF THE CDC
AND THE FDA AND BUT IN THIS BOOK HERE EVERY AMERICAN SHOULD
READ THE LIGHT AND THE GLORY AND IT GETS INTO THESE
PROVIDENTIAL THINGS. WOW A MINUTE AND A HALF LEFT SO
I PROBABLY WON'T HAVE TIME TO READ WHAT I WANTED TO READ.
>> BUT THE THING IS IS I'VE MADE STATEMENTS THAT 1776
REALLY DOES IN 2300 YEARS FROM WHEN THE TEMPLE WAS DESTROYED
WHICH FULFILLED THE PROPHECY IN DANIEL EIGHT VERSE 14 BUT I
HAVEN'T PROVED YET OKAY IF YOU GOOGLE WHEN WAS SOLOMON'S
TEMPLE DESTROYED IT'LL SAY 587 B.C. BUT ALL BC DATES ARE
BOGUS. THE WE DON'T KNOW WHEN HE WAS
BORN. WE DO KNOW WHEN HE WAS BAPTIZED
AND IF YOU ARRANGE YOUR CHRONOLOGY FROM THE YEAR HE WAS
BAPTIZED WHICH WAS 28 WHICH CORRESPONDS WITH THE 15TH YEAR
OF TIBERIUS CAESAR YOU'LL YOU'LL KNOW THAT I'M NOT
BLOWING SMOKE. I'M TELLING YOU REALITY.
AND EVEN THOUGH PETER MARSHALL AND DAVID EMANUEL DIDN'T KNOW
THIS, THEY CERTAINLY WOULD HAVE PUT IT IN THEIR BOOK.
>> THAT MEANS ISRAEL AND THE UNITED STATES ARE THE ONLY TWO
NATIONS AND WE ARE THAT ARE IN THE BIBLE.
WE LIVE HERE. WHAT A BLESSED THING TO LIVE
HERE AND SO ANYWAY, JUST THINK ABOUT IT IF IF JESUS WAS
BAPTIZED AT THE END OF THE 69TH SEATTLE CYCLE WHICH
CORRESPONDED TO 20 EIGHT A.D. AND THE DECLARATION BY CYRUS
WAS GIVEN 70 YEARS AFTER THE EXILE, WOULDN'T THAT MEAN IT
WAS 79 SEMITIC CYCLES 553 YEARS BIBI BEFORE BAPTISM FORGET THE
B.C IT'S BIBI OR B AFTER BAPTISM ALL CHRONOLOGY OH RIGHT
. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
WELCOME. >> I HAVEN'T DONE THIS BEFORE.
I HAVEN'T DONE THIS BEFORE SO I'M GOING TO TRY TO BE SURE I
WAS PRESENT WITH YOUR PRESENTATION AND THEN BEFORE I
CAME HERE I WAS AT THE COMMISSION FOR UTILITIES AND I
NOTICED THAT WITH MY FIELD ANALYSIS THAT I HAD CONDUCTED
IN THE CITY THERE'S MAYBE A DISCREPANCY THAT MIGHT BE
OVERLOOKED THAT I'M TRYING TO BRING INTO FOCUS AND IT'S TRUE
THE FACT THAT WELL YOU HAD MENTIONED IS YOU'RE BUILDING
AFFORDABLE HOUSING ON LAND THAT WAS ALLOCATED FOR SMALL
BUSINESS AND THE CONTRACTORS P, G AND E FOR MY FIELD ANALYSIS
THEY SAID THAT THE PIPES THAT THEY'RE PUTTING IN OR THEY HAVE
PUT IN IT TO ALLOCATED FOR THE RESOURCE AND THE DEMAND FOR
THAT SPECIFIC LOCATION. AND SO MY SKETCH HERE WILL SHOW
YOU THAT LIKE A THREE PERSON HOUSEHOLD OR A BUSINESS THAT'S
SUPPOSED TO BE MEETING A DEMAND FOR THE LIKE THE WATER AND THE
SEWAGE IF YOU BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING ON IT, IT MIGHT
POTENTIALLY BE OR IT MIGHT OVER STRAIN THE SEWAGE AND THAT IS
CAUSING THE OTHER ISSUES THAT PEOPLE ARE COMPLAINING ABOUT.
SO I HOPE THAT YOU TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION AND THEY DID SAY
THAT THE CONTRACTORS THAT IT WOULD COST MORE TO REPLACE THE
IT WOULD REPLACE IT WOULD COST MORE TO REPLACE THE PIPES.
>> SO IF YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE AFFORDABLE HOUSING ON TOP OF
SMALL PIPES THAT ARE REQUIRED FOR SMALL DEMAND, IT'S GOING TO
CAUSE A SEWAGE ISSUE. I THINK THAT CONCLUDES IT.
OH MY MY SOLUTION WAS TO PROVIDE US STANDARDIZATION ON
OCCUPANCY LIMITS WITH CONCURRENT WITH THE PUNY DATA
SETS THEM THEY MIGHT GET IF I EXPLAINED IT WELL.
OKAY THANKS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
THIS AFTERNOON. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
ALL RIGHT. SEEING NONE MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE. AGENDA ITEMS 25 THROUGH 32 YES
ITEMS 25 THROUGH 32 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION BUT
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE. UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR
ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE. >> SURPRISE MILKER.
THANK YOU. I WOULD LIKE TO BE ADDED AS A
CO-SPONSOR TO NUMBER 26 AND 32. >> THANK YOU.
AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS
25 THROUGH 32 AND ITEMS 25 THROUGH 32.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MANAGEMENT I'M SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR
SORTER SORTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR REN GADO AND GADO I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I THERE ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE
ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS AND TO REPORT MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. AND COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM? >> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT MANDEL MEN FOR THE LATE MR. PETER KANE
AND ON A MOTION MADE BY SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND PRESIDENT
MANDEL MEANT TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
FOR THE FORMER CHAIR OF THE CALIFORNIA DEMOCRATIC PARTY,
FORMER MEMBER OF THE CALIFORNIA STATE SENATE, TWO TIME MEMBER
OF THE CALIFORNIA STATE ASSEMBLY AND FOR FORMER MEMBER
OF THE U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES THE HONORABLE
JOHN BURTON. >> AND I THINK THAT BRINGS US
TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA, MADAM CLERK.
DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED